<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The first part of the consideration of humane condition vvherin is contained the morall consideration of a mans selfe: as what, who, and what manner of man he is. Written by I.P. Esquier.</title>
            <author>Perrott, James, Sir, 1571-1637.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1600</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09490</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19773</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114574</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849799</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849799</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14967</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09490)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14967)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1252:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The first part of the consideration of humane condition vvherin is contained the morall consideration of a mans selfe: as what, who, and what manner of man he is. Written by I.P. Esquier.</title>
                  <author>Perrott, James, Sir, 1571-1637.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 60 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Joseph Barnes, and are to be sold [by J. Broome in London] in Paules Church-yard, at the signe of the Bible,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1600.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the indifferent and friendly reader" signed: Iames Perrott.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The consideration of humane condition.</note>
                  <note>No more published.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Psychology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14967:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14967:1"/>
            <p>THE FIRST PART OF THE CONSIDE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RATION OF HV<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Condition:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVHERIN IS CONTAINED the Morall Conſideration of a mans ſelfe: as what, who, and what manner of man he is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Written by I.P. Eſquier.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Amo vt invenio.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>AT OXFORD,</hi> Printed by Joſeph Barnes, and are to be ſold in Paules Church-yard, at the ſigne of the Bible. 1600.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14967:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14967:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, HIS VERY ESPECIAL GOOD LORD, THOMAS Baron of Buckhurſt, Lord Treaſurer of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, one of the LL. of her Maieſties moſt Honorable privie Counſaile, Knight of the Honorable Order of <hi>the Garter, and Chauncellour of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſitie of Oxford,</hi> I.P. <hi>wiſheth encreaſe of honour and eternall faelicitie.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the fore-front of this ſmall and ſlender building, many thinges are wanting (Right Honorable, and my moſt honored Lord) which through the diſtraction of buſines, the ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of time, and the vnskilfulnes of the builder could not be finiſhed, as it was purpoſed. For the ſame for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune falleth out many times vnto writers of bookes, as doth vnto Builders of houſes: when as in both, at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the worke, they, which frame the firſt founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and plot, doe propoſe vnto themſelues leſſe labor and expence of time, then in the ende they muſt beſtow, before it be fully finiſhed: So, ſometimes they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to leaue their well-begunne labours without any ende, or elſe rudely and roughly to finiſh the ſame. Such is the concluſion in the firſt part of this poore cottage of <hi>Conſideration,</hi> which I haue builded like an vnexperien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced workeman, and which I haue preſumed humbly to
<pb facs="tcp:14967:3"/>offer vnto your Lordſhips Honorable patronage, not ſo much for the worth of the worke, as to teſtifie the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgement of my moſt zealous faith and affection vnto your Lordſhippe, being therevnto bound by your Lordſhips honorable favour and furtheraunces. For which I can yeelde no other offering, but the fruits of this my yet vnperfected labours, with the continuance of my vowed devotion (next to my moſt gracious Soveraigne) to doe your Lordſhip ſervice. And ſo I humbly end, with my praiers for your Lordſhips preſervation and increaſe of honours.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Haroldston</hi> 
                  <date>the 16. <hi>of Novemb.</hi> 1600.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt bounden, and ever to be commaunded, <hi>I.P.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:14967:3"/>
            <head>To the indifferent and friendly Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Know that they, vvhich publiſh any thinge in writing vnto the worlde, doe ſubmitte them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues vnto common cenſure. And I am not ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that as it is more eaſie to finde a fault in things done, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to doe the ſame ſo ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially, as no faulte ſhall be founde therewith: ſo is it more eaſie to amend, then to make. If therefore I haue erred in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing (as I acknowledge no ſuch excellency in mee, but that I may eaſily miſtake) Let accuſtomed community of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring excuſe me amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt others. For, <hi>humanu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt errare.</hi> And if he that pervſeth this Tracte, do find any faultes therin, I ſhall deſire the direction of his better iudgment to amend them; vvhich I vvilleſteeme as a very greate favour. I commend this <hi>firſt parte of Conſideration</hi> to thy honeſt and diſcreet construction. It containeth the <hi>Morall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of a mans ſelfe.</hi> There are three other pointes of Conſideration by mee intended to bee publiſhed: the next vvhereof is the <hi>Politicall Conſideration of thoſe thinges, that are vnder vs.</hi> The thirde is the <hi>Naturall Conſideration of thoſe thinges, that are about vs.</hi> The fourth and laste is the <hi>Metaphyſicall Conſideration of thoſe thinges, that are aboue vs.</hi> This firſt, vvhich is here publiſhed, I haue offered as a taſte of my labours, and a triall of thy good or ill allovvance; if it bee accepted with
<pb facs="tcp:14967:4"/>as good meaning, as it vvas offered, and that the honorable Perſonage, to vvhome this is dedicated (and to vvhome all the rest of my labors are due doe not direct the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie; I vvill proceede as ſpeedily, as conveniently I can, to publiſh the reſt. But if this yeelde thee any diſtaſte, or bee diſliked; it is but ſo much labour loſt in that, vvhich is al ready done, and ſo much labour ſaued, in that, vvhich ſhould be hereafter done. So as thou wiſheſt vvell, farevvell.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my houſe at Haroldſtone <date>the <hi>16.</hi> of November.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>The well willer of them, that wiſh well. IAMES PERROTT.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14967:4"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>THE CONSIDERATION</hi> of humane Condition.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. 1.</hi> How neceſsary, and what Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration is.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Lants haue but a <hi>Vegetatiue</hi> faculty, and beaſts haue but a <hi>Senſitiue</hi> power to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce thoſe effects which nature (or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the guider of natures workes) hath ordained them to execute in their ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall kindes: but man alone (aboue all the reſt) hath the moſt excellent helpe of <hi>Reaſon</hi> to order his affections, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verne his thoughts, and his deedes. Why ſhould not man then (ſo farre. exceeding all other creatures in this moſt admirable and powerfull gift of <hi>Reaſon</hi>) expell thereby all the perverſe paſſions, the beaſtiall luſtes, and the fonde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of the minde: which many times make him inferiour to the moſt vile and moſt contemptible creatures of the world? If vve would know the reaſon of this ſo great an evill, it is becauſe he doth ſeldome accompany his actions with <hi>Conſideration,</hi> which is the chiefe ruler and governeſſe vnder <hi>Reaſon:</hi> for where <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration</hi> doth not firſt open the dore, and make the firſt ente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance into any action of accompt, there commonly the ſucceſſe is ſuch as breedeth but ſorrow, ſhame, and confuſion: and where due <hi>Conſideration</hi> commeth before, and with our deedes, it is ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome ſeene there, but that the event falleth out according to our expectation. This being ſo, it were not amiſſe to looke ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what into this glaſſe of <hi>Conſideration,</hi> therein to behold (as neere as we may) the mappe and character of humane Condition.</p>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:14967:5"/>
                  <p>And becauſe conſideration is founde to bee a matter of ſo great moment in directing the courſe of every mans life, as that it may iuſtly be called the loadſtone of mans life: it were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient firſt to know what this conſideration is, before wee en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deuoure to iudge of the effects thereof.</p>
                  <p>Conſideration (as <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> doth define it) is the ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding,<note place="margin">Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</note> or the proceſſe of Reaſon pertaining to the contemplation of the trueth. <hi>Conſideration</hi> therefore is more generall,<note place="margin">Cogitatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Meditatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> &amp; more profitable then is Cogitation, or Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. For <hi>Cogitation</hi> is but a particular power of collecting in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dividuall intentions: and <hi>Meditation,</hi> but an inwarde behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, buſied in the inquiſition of thinges: but this our <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration,</hi> is the operation of all the vnderſtanding: as hath beene already defined.<note place="margin">Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation. Delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> Likewiſe ſome alleadge that <hi>Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation</hi> belongeth onely to divine thinges. And Deliberation properly appertaineth to humane and political matters: but this our <hi>Conſideration</hi> doeth comprehend both, or at the leaſt is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſant in both.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> Why ſome men are more given to Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then others.</head>
                  <p>THe cauſes that ſome men are more deliberate, and more conſideratiue in their actions then others, are diverſe: ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther proceeding from the well or evill ſituation of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriour ſenſes; or ariſing from the good, or badde conſtitution of their complexions; or comming of the company that they moſt commonly keepe, and the exerciſe that they do chiefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſe.</p>
                  <p>As touching the firſt,<note place="margin">The firſt cauſe.</note> which is the ſituation and due proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the interiour ſenſes: how much that doth availe to the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of Conſideration, by this we may conceiue; that as the ſenſes haue their ſeveral ſeates in the braines, ſo do they receiue their temperature, according to the temperature of that parte,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14967:5"/>wherein they are placed, and there-after are men made apte or vnapt to enter into due Conſideration.</p>
                  <p>As for example, the firſt of the interiour ſences (which both Philoſophers and Phiſitions doe call the <hi>common ſenſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. Common ſenſe.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is common to all the exteriour ſenſes to convaigh their ſhapes and formes vnto it) is placed in the forepart of the braine, having a ſeverall cell or roome, in which the fiue nerues (com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming from the fiue exteriour ſenſes) doe meete, if this bee not conveniently moiſt, and of a convenient quantity, it cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the right ſhape of theſe, and conſequently the other ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes cannot concurre to conſider aright thereof.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond ſenſe is called the <hi>Imaginatiue ſenſe,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue ſenſe. Although Ariſtotle maketh no mention of this Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginatiue ſenſe, yet I thought good here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in to follow other Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers, who doe make this diſtinct fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other three.</note> which alſo is placed in the fore-part of the braine next vnto the Common ſenſe: and the office thereof is to containe &amp; retaine the formes of thoſe things, which the exteriour ſenſes doe preſent vnto the Common ſenſe: for that the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſenſe of it ſelfe conſiſteth meerely of moiſture, which is apt to receiue, but not to retaine: and this Imaginatiue ſenſe is compoſed of drineſſe, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth the figures of thinges more firmely: therefore if this ſenſe hath not alſo his right quality and condition, the true ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes of thinges ſenſible cannot be well conſerved to be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered of.</p>
                  <p>The next is called the <hi>Phantaſie</hi> (or as ſome ſay) the <hi>Eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue ſenſe,</hi> which is placed in the middle part of the braine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Common ſenſe and the Memory: this ſenſe ſerueth to compoſe, to devide, and to diſtinguiſh of the ſhapes, which are preſented vnto the Common ſenſe, and preſerued by the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maginatiue ſenſe;<note place="margin">3 Pha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taſie.</note> and this ſenſe is ſeated in the middle parte of the heade, as a cel to receiue thoſe figures from the Common ſenſe and Imaginatiue, as to take them againe out of the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory being the ſtore-houſe of the head: it is compoſed of heat, by which it is in much motion, and into it doe reſort all the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſpirites, but if it doe exceede an ordinary temperature of heate, it maketh too much motion in the braine, and leaueth no liberty to a ſetled Conſideration.</p>
                  <p>The laſt of the interiour ſenſes, is the <hi>Memory,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">4 Memory.</note> which is pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14967:6"/>in the hinder parte of the head: the cell and ſituation of this ſenſe is more dry, and ſomewhat harder then the reſt of the braine, becauſe (as it vvas ſaide before) that drynes is the cauſe of Retention, ſo this ſenſe beeing made to retaine the ſhape of things, vvhich are delivered from the Common ſenſe vnto the Imaginatiue, but alſo the Memory muſt retaine the ſhapes of intentions, vvhich the Imaginatiue doeth preſent vnto it: ſo as it is truely tearmed the Treaſury of the minde: and therefore if the Memory haue not his iuſt proportion of dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes neither exceeding nor vvanting much thereof, then it cannot retaine well; and ſo the Conſideration (which is not only a Meſſenger, but as it were a Counſellour betwixt the Memory &amp; the reſt of the Senſes) ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not receiue his right courſe.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond cauſe,<note place="margin">The ſecond cauſe,</note> vvhich we ſaide firſt did much helpe, or hinder our Conſideration, is the Conſtitution of the fovvre <hi>Complexions</hi> according to the operation of the fowre <hi>Elements</hi> in mans body: for the Phyloſophers affirme that the temperature of the minde, followeth the temperature of the body: and the temperature of the body conſiſteth in the Compoſition of the foure Complexions, vvhich receiue and participate the qualities of the foure Elements; as for example; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the <hi>ſanguine Complexion</hi> doth participate with the Element of the aire, which is by nature hotte and moiſt: theſe two qualities in the <hi>ſanguine Complexion</hi> do worke this operation, that it cauſeth a ready conceipt, but it doth divert the mind from any deepe Conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Alſo the <hi>Phlegmaticke Complexion,</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſting of colde and moi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſture, hath this property, that by reaſon of over much coldnes, it doth dull the ſpirites, whereby they cannot aptly conceiue; and becauſe of much moiſture, it cannot retaine what is received: therefore it is vnapt for Conſideration.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The <hi>cholericke</hi> which doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſt of heate and drynes is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more apte to conceiue then the Phlegmati<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cke, and yet in that the heate is not mixed with either colde or moiſture to qualifie the ſame, it doth not plant any firme leaſure to conſider what is to be done.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The <hi>melancholicke Complexion,</hi> that is made of colde and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14967:6"/>drynes, (vvhich in their natures doe make a better mixture of moderation) doth plante a firme leaſure to conſider what is to be done, and therefore is fitteſt for Conſideration.</p>
                  <p>Beſides this abſolute predomination of each of theſe firſt foure <hi>Qualities</hi> in mens bodies, vvhereby they are made either apte or vnable for Conſideration ſometimes; there is a mixture of the <hi>Complexion</hi> in one body in ſuch ſorte that it can hardly be ſaide which of two hath the greateſt power or predominancy, and then there is many times the beſt temperature in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and conſequently the minde is more apte for Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and the life of man is longer preſerued. As for example; vvhen the <hi>cholericke</hi> and <hi>phlegmaticke</hi> Complexions are ſo mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that the <hi>cholericke</hi> hath ſome what the ſuperiour power, and the <hi>phlegmaticke</hi> is proportioned vnto it, then the drynes of the one doth ſomevvhat qualifie the over-much moiſtnes of the other, vvhereby this temperature maketh a man more apte for Conſideration. So <hi>ſanguine</hi> and <hi>melancholy,</hi> being mixed in ſuch ſort as the <hi>ſanguine</hi> in ſome ſmall degree doth ſurmount the <hi>melancholy,</hi> it maketh a more even proportion of the foure firſt <hi>Qualities</hi> in one body: by which compoſition (and as they call it a Communicating of the contrary qualities in the foure Elementes) there is made a reconciliation of their contrary effectes, and a coniunction of their forces, whereby the minde of man is more fitte for Conſideration.<note place="margin">The thirde cauſe.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The third cauſe which helpeth or hindereth Conſideration is (as hath beene before alleadged) the <hi>Company,</hi> which we keepe, and the <hi>Studies</hi> which we vſe: for though theſe fore-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited cauſes may be greate helpes or hinderances to our Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, as the ſituation of the ſenſes, and the conſtitution of the complexions, as being inſtrumental cauſes of Conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet theſe may bee aptely diſpoſed, and yet Conſideration in ſome ſorte may be wanting. For as we ſee inſtrumentes, which are excellentlie compoſed, and haue in themſelues a verie ſweete ſounde, if they bee vvell tuned and vvell played on; yet if he that ſhoulde play thereon doth not perfourme his parte; either by reaſon of the company, with whome he is, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:14967:7"/>doth more attend their actions, then his owne play; or elſe, by meanes of ſome other actions he hath in hand, doth not exqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitely vſe and exerciſe his skill; then the inſtrument, on which he playeth, looſeth the ſweetneſſe of his ſounde, and the true vſe thereof: ſo is it in the vſe of Conſideration; for although the interiour ſenſes bee well ſeated, and the complexions wel compoſed, which are as inſtrumentes of the minde, yet if the minde it ſelfe be not by good company and good exerciſe well ſettled to Conſideration, theſe inſtrumentes looſe the ſweete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of their ſounde, and the effectes of Conſideration by them cannot haue a right courſe. For proofe hereof; firſt, to beginne with company &amp; converſation of good or evil men, how much the one helpeth &amp; the other hindereth Conſideration, we may ſee by the example of ſundry younge men, who of their owne diſpoſitions haue beene civill, diſcreete, and well inclined to Conſideration, vntill that they comming into euill company haue by imitating their light behaviour beene brought to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>togither careleſſe and vnconſiderate:<note place="margin">Eccleſ. 13.</note> It is true, that <hi>hee which toucheth pitch, ſhall bee defiled therewith,</hi> and that he, which kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth ill company, ſhal be in the ende carried from all good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration.<note place="margin">Pſalm. 18.</note> For <hi>with the good</hi> (as it is ſaid) <hi>then ſhalt learne goodneſſe, and with the perverſe thou ſhalt be perverted.</hi> Againe we ſee on the other ſide, that the company and converſation of graue, learned &amp; conſiderate men doth much mooue vs vnto the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their behaviour, and by their example wee learne the like to become conſiderate as they are: and by the counſaile of ſuch graue men many times the raſh and vnſtaied humors of youth are tempered and tuned to the right meane &amp; meaſure of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration: as <hi>Catoes</hi> graue converſation was not onely a lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne, but alſo a leſſon (for all thoſe that knew him) to learne conſideration.</p>
                  <p>Now laſtly for exerciſe,<note place="margin">The fourth cauſe.</note> how that doeth helpe or hinder the courſe of our Conſideration, wee may conceiue it by knowing that exerciſe is of two ſortes; either of the body, or of the mind: the exerciſe of the body we cal Labour, the exerciſe of the mind we call Study. For the firſt, which is the exerciſe of the body, we
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14967:7"/>finde that this being moderately vſed maketh the body ſtrong and healthy, whereby the minde is alſo made more free to full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill his functions, eſpecially in the courſe of Conſideration: but if the body bee over-laboured, it breedeth a wearineſſe and a weakeneſſe in the partes thereof, whereby alſo the minde is mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſted, &amp; leſſe at liberty to enter into Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration what ought to be done. Likewiſe for Study, it hath the like or greater ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, then Labor hath, in making the minde fit or vnfit for Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration: becauſe we haue it in dayly experience, that mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Study doth inlighten the mind, &amp; kindle the pure bright-ſhining fire of Conſideration. Yea many times it hath the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to divert mens mindes from evil cogitations, and to convert them vnto the due conſideration of themſelues and of thoſe thinges, that belonge vnto them.<note place="margin">Xenoph de dict. &amp; fact. <hi>Socrat.</hi>
                     </note> As <hi>Socrates</hi> ſaid vnto a skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Phyſiognomer, who tolde him that hee was a man of a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked diſpoſition, (whereat others laughed knowing the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) it is true ſaid <hi>Socrates</hi> which thou telleſt me that by nature I was wicked and of a lewd condition, but by my ſtudy, learning, and conſideration, I haue corrected thoſe evill conditions. So we ſee that moderate Exerciſe, and moderate Study doe much availe to the attaining of Conſideration, &amp; of thoſe good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions which do follow Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration. But on the contrary, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate Study doth much ſpende the ſpirits and weaken the braine, whereby the courſe of due Conſideration is very much hindered.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> 
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto what we ſhoulde apply the ſcope of our Conſideration.</head>
                  <p>NOW having ſaide ſomewhat how neceſſary, and what conſideration is, as alſo what thinges doe moſt helpe or hinder this Conſideration; it commeth next in order to ſhew vnto what wee ought chiefly to bende the courſe of our Conſideration. Wherein we may beholde by the example of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14967:8"/>other mens behaviours, that moſt men are very carefull and doe vſe very great Conſideration in the compaſſing of thoſe things which they do deſire moſt. As for example, the covetous man doth labour all the power of his Conſideration to attaine vnto riches. The ambitious man doth enter into Conſideration of no onething ſo much, as how to come to preferment, and to obtaine dignities and honour. The laſcivious man doth ſtraine the ſtringes of his Conſideration only to compaſle his pleaſures. So that theſe men (and others of all conditions) ſeeme to vſe no Conſideration in any thing, but only on that, which they deſire moſt, and about which they apply all their care and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry, leaving all other thinges, as matters (in their opinions) of no moment: when as perchance that, vvhich they ſo much ſeeke after, and doe ſo carefully imploy all their Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons about, in other mens conſtructions may be of no ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, and worthy of no great Conſideration: As the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous man doth admire why the ambitious do bend their whole Conſideration about the ſeeking of honours, great authority, great names and preheminence: which the covetous accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth but as blaſtes of winde, blowne away with the breath of mens mouthes: on the other ſide, the ambitious man recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth of the covetous man, but as of one, that is baſe minded, becauſe hee beſtoweth all his Conſideration to procure him wealth without vſing the ſame to any other purpoſe then to pinch himſelfe and his poore neighboures, not knowing vvho ſhall enioy them after his deceaſe, or whither hee ſhall haue them himſelfe as long as he liveth. Likewiſe the laſcivious man laugheth at both the covetous man and the ambitious: &amp; they both as much at him, whom they deeme altogither vnconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, in that he hath no other Conſideration of any matter, which doeth concerne him moſt, but only his vaine pleaſure, which they can ſay he doth moſt commonly purchaſe with repentance of his time miſpent, his health decaied and his hability conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: ſo that we ſee moſt men doe miſlike the courſe of other mens Conſiderations, and few doe take the right courſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues of due Conſideration, becauſe al do aime at an end, which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14967:8"/>they thinke ſhoulde bee good vnto themſelues: but there is a goodnes, which is in <hi>appearaunce</hi> onely, but not indeede: and there is a goodnes <hi>on truth,</hi> &amp; <hi>on ſubſtance,</hi> without vaine ſhewe. Now to the attaining of this goodnes (which is true goodnes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede) ought our Conſideration to be directed: and for effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting thereof,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bernard de Conſid ad Eugen.</hi> We ought to conſider foure thinges.</note> we muſt follow the courſe &amp; counſell of <hi>Bernard</hi> in his foure bookes of <hi>Conſideration</hi> written to <hi>Eugenius,</hi> vvhome hee vvilleth to conſider chiefely theſe foure thinges: <hi>firſt, thy ſelfe: nexte, thoſe thinges that are vnder thee: then, thoſe thinges that are aboute thee: and laſtly, thoſe thinges that are aboue thee. In conſidering thy ſelfe</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thou muſt learne to knovve, What thou art: VVhoe thou art: and, VVhat manner of man thou art.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                     <hi>In conſidering What thou art, thou ſhalt find in Nature that thou art a man, that is Reaſonable and Mortall: being Mortall, thou maieſt be ſorie: but beeing Reaſonable, thou haſte cauſe to mittigate thy ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                     <hi>In the conſideration of thy ſelfe VVho thou arte,</hi>
                     <hi>thou muſt finde out the perfect foote-ſteppes of thy parentage, thy calling, and thy ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
                     <hi>In conſidering VVhat manner of man thou art,</hi>
                     <hi>thou ſhalt ſeeke out thy naturall inclination, thy conditions, qualities, and the courſe of thy life.</hi> In this ſorte doth <hi>Bernard</hi> beginne a briefe, apte, and an excellent entraunce into the moſt profitable pointes of Conſideration. Firſt, hee beginneth vvith that pointe of Conſideration vvhich concerneth the <hi>Knowledge of thy ſelfe,</hi> being the beginning of all true knowledge, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this no knowledge or conſideration can profit thee, be it of matters never ſo exquiſite, or of myſteries never ſo high. For as it doth concerne every man to learne what is done at home, before hee goe abroad: ſo doth it behoue him to knovve himſelfe, before hee looke into others. It is true that many men ſeeme to knovve many thinges, and yet, not knowing themſelues, they knovve nothing at all: or at leaſt, they knovve nothinge in that, which doth moſt availe them.</p>
                  <pb n="10" facs="tcp:14967:9"/>
                  <p>Concerning theſe circumſtances of Conſideration, <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome</hi> goeth ſomewhat farther in wordes, though not much far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in effect, then <hi>Bernard</hi> doth. He ſaith, that <hi>it doth behooue euerte vviſe man to conſider vvhat himſelfe is, vvhat is vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in him, vvhat is belovve him, vvhat is aboue him, vvhat is againſt him, what is before him, and what is after him: all which Conſiderations</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>) <hi>bring forth a fowre-folde fruite: as; Profite to thy ſelfe, Charity tovvardes thy neighbours, Contempt of the worlde, and the loue of God.</hi> This diviſion though it differ ſome what in wordes from the former, yet it is the ſame in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and effect.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. 4.</hi> The Conſideration of thy ſelfe what thou are in thy Creation.</head>
                  <p>IT is neceſſary to proſecute the firſt diviſion of the pointes of Conſideration, laid downe by <hi>Bernard,</hi> ſome what more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly then he did, becauſe he applyed all his exhortations therein vnto the perſon and profeſſion of <hi>Eugenius,</hi> then Pope of Rome, as particular inſtructions for his place &amp; calling. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it were not amiſſe in this our Conſideration of humane co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, to amplifie ſomewhat on the condition of humane eſtate in generall, and of every kinde of eſtate in particular (as neere as we may) without offence of any, and yet for the inſtruction of all: obſerving ſtill and ſtrictly thoſe members of diviſion, which this learned Father hath laide down, to direct vs vnto the perfecteſt pointes of Conſideration. To this purpoſe it beho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth to begin with the Creation of man, wherein we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what he is: vvhereof, if any doe aske the Philoſophers, they wil deliver divers contrary opinions: And to beginne with <hi>Anaximander</hi> hee alleadged, that man was firſt made of the earth and of vvater, vvhich tvvo Elements (as hee affirmed) were tempered and ſhaped vvith the heate of the ſunne. Then <hi>Empedocles</hi> conceived that all the members of man vvere made
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14967:9"/>of the earth, and that all the other Elements (as hee coniectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) did concurre to frame and faſhion the ſame: as the fire to giue heate, the vvater to yeelde moiſture, and the aire to ſende ſpirit vnto the reſt. But omitting all vaine coniectures, &amp; ſuch like fabulous inventions of <hi>Prometheus</hi> fire, <hi>Deucalions</hi> ſtones, vvhich the Poets fained to bee the cauſes, or the cauſers of mans Creation: let vs levell firſt (in the conſideration of mans Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) vvith the more certaine groundes of Philoſophy in this point, and then conclude with the vndoubted verity of the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred hiſtory.</p>
                  <p>Some Philoſophers doe define <hi>Creation</hi> to be <hi>a proceſſe or a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion from that which was not, to that which is:</hi> or elſe, <hi>from nothing, to ſomething; when as yet there were no matter to bee preſuppoſed out of which it might be made.</hi> This opinion, as it is contrary to that of other Philoſophers, which ſaid that,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>1.</hi> Phyſ. c. <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Ex nihilo nihil fit;</hi> that is, <hi>of nothing, nothing is made:</hi> ſo it draweth neareſt to the truth, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeth beſt vvith the infallible authority of the holy Scripture, vvhich ſaith that <hi>the world was made of nothing,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Gen. 1.1. Eccl. 10.9.12. Wiſd. 11.14</note> by the word of the ever-living <hi>worde,</hi> vvithout any other foreknowne matter ſaue only Gods word, his vvill, and his vviſedome: and of this no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing (made ſomething) was man at the firſt created, as holy writte doth teſtifie: for hee was made of no other moulde then of the duſt of the earth, a weake and ſlender beginning for a high and hauty minde, but moſt fit, to ſet forth the great might, of the almighty Creator.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. 5.</hi> The Conſideration of thy ſelfe what thou art in thy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, and naturall Conſtitution.</head>
                  <p>THe next Conſideration after thy Creation, is, the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of thy <hi>Conception,</hi> and of thy <hi>naturall Procreation,</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution of body:</hi> wherein, if thou wilt know vvhat thou art: firſt conſider that by the fall of thy firſt Parents (who were purely Created without any Corruption) their diſobeying
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14967:10"/>of their Creators commaundement, cauſed the curſe to fall on them, &amp; on their poſterity: whereby not only they but, for their ſake, the earth &amp; all other creatures were ſubiect to the curſe, ſo that of a pure Creation (by mans tranſgreſſion) became an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pure Generation. And that thou maieſt farther conſider what thou art in this kind of <hi>generation</hi> (or as we cal it <hi>Conception</hi>) learne that <hi>generation is a beginning to be that, which it was not, but by vvay of mutation of one forme into another.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now to come more neere vnto the Conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thy ſelfe what thou art in this thy Generatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or Procreatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; if one ſhould aske thee, how thou waſt conceived? and how thou cameſt into the world? thou wilt (it may be) anſwere, even as other men did, &amp; do: I was begotten of my father, &amp; borne of my mother. Yea but how is that? not to rip vp the ſecrets of nature (for that wold rather ſavour of immodeſty, then farther thee in the due Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of thy ſelfe what thou art:) thou maiſt know that thou hadſt but a meane beginning of Conception (be thy birth never ſo great) and know thou, that thou haddeſt no other meanes of Procreation, then the meaneſt man living, for thou waſt (what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer thou art) conceived without honour, delivered with vvo, &amp; that with the great danger of her, that brought thee into the world: ſo that, though we omit the manner of thy firſt fourming in thy mothers womb (where of thou oughteſt to take no pride) yet <hi>Plinie</hi> the moſt excellent naturall Philoſopher,<note place="margin">Plin. natur. hiſt. lib. 7.</note> and moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite Secretary of natures workes, will tell thee; that beaſts are not bound in chaines, when they are borne, but thou man art moſt vnhappily borne with thy hands and thy feete bound, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning the world with puniſhment: <hi>O madneſſe of man</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>thinking that of theſe beginnings he is borne to be prowde, when as the firſt hope of ſtrength, and the firſt, gift of time maketh him like to a fowre feoted beaſt: for hee is forced on his armes and legges, being not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe able to ſtande or goe:</hi> This ſaith <hi>Plinie</hi> of thy birth. But if thou wilt enter farther into Conſideration of thy <hi>naturall Conſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> of body after thou art borne, thou ſhalt finde that as thou arte borne naked, ſo thou doſt ſtil of thy ſelfe remaine naked, having by nature no other covering or any defenſe ſaue only thy bare
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14967:10"/>body, but that thou doſt borrow helps of other creatures, which thou accoumpteſt but as baſe and vile: for thou cloatheſt &amp; kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt thy ſelfe warme with garmentes made of wooll, being but the covering of ſilly ſheepe: with skinnes, the naturall garments of bruit beaſts: thou deckeſt thy ſelfe with ſilke, being but the excrements of poore wormes; with flowres, being but the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grovving of vvilde fields: vvith ſtones, being but the of-ſcow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the earth, of the ſea, and of rockes: all which the needy naked man doth borrow of beaſts, and of other creatures, to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, to maintaine, &amp; to adorne his weake and al wanting body. But thou, not being content to vſe the helpe of thoſe naturall creatures for the ſupply of thy natural defects, doſt yet therwith take occaſion to grovv provvde; like the begger, vvho having borrowed a new coate, ſhould therewith preſently fal into liking of himſelfe &amp; ſcorne al the reſt of his fellowe beggers. So doth the naked vnconſiderat man borrow of birds, feathers; of beaſts, skins, wooll, vvith other coverings; of both birds and beaſts, the fleſh to feed him; he borroweth ſavours &amp; ornaments of flowres; of fruits, ſuſtena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; of thoſe things which come out of the earth, beauty &amp;c. And having al theſe helpes not of himſelfe, but of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther creatures, he vſeth them as inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts to increaſe his pride, rather then to ſuſtaine his neceſſities. This might ſerue in the Conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thy ſelfe, vvhat thou art according to thy <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Conſtitution of birth and of body,</hi> to teach thee hovv vveake, and hovv vnprovided, how meane, and how needy thou art by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: vvhereby thou maieſt profitably learne <hi>humiliation,</hi> and to abate that provvde conceite, vvhich good ſucceſſe and proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity might plant in thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. 6.</hi> The Conſideration of thy ſelfe what thou art in the fruition of this ſhort and vncertaine life.</head>
                  <p>AFter thy birth &amp; conſtitution of body, the Conſideration of this <hi>lifes fruitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> craveth place: wherin if thou wilt know, what thou art, conſider firſt how ſhort this life is. Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14967:11"/>this it is true, which one ſaith, that <hi>nothing doth deceiue men ſo much, as that they are ignorant how ſhorte a space they haue to liue, and therefore doe alwaies promiſe vnto themſelues a longer time to liue.</hi> And as an vnſeaſonable yeare doth either parch the leaues of trees by reaſon of exceſſiue heate and drought, ſo that they wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and fall away, or by extreame colde are conſumed, or by bluſtering ſtormes are blowen of: ſo doth any extraordinary di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemperature either of heate or colde, drynes or moiſture de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, or at the leaſt indaunger the life of man. And if thou doubt heereof, the Phyſitions will tell their opinions plainely, that there are foure faculties by which the life of man is maintained, and that if any of theſe foure faculties doe miſſe his force and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, then mans life preſently periſheth. The firſt, is the <hi>Attractiue facultie,</hi> by which the nouriſhment is drawen into the partes nouriſhed: that conſiſteth of heate and drines: and if any of theſe two doe abounde or be deficient, then preſentely the <hi>Attractiue</hi> looſeth his office, and the life of man is mightely indaungered.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond faculty is the <hi>Retentiue,</hi>whereby the nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment attracted is retained vntill it be digeſted: this conſiſteth of cold and drines; and if either of theſe qualities be not alwaies rightly proportioned, the <hi>Retentiue faculty</hi> faileth of his force, and then the life of man is likewiſe in perill.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third is the <hi>Digeſtiue faculty,</hi>by which the attractiue and the retained nouriſhment is digeſted: this conſiſteth of heate and moiſture, the which two qualities, if they be not well con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditioned, then alſo the life of man cannot long continue.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth is the <hi>Expulſiue faculty,</hi>by which all ſuperfluities are eiected: this conſiſteth of colde and moiſture, which if they be not moderately mixed, then the <hi>expulſiue faculty</hi> cannot per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme his force, and ſo the excreaments which ſhould be expel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, doe turne into inward corruption, whereby the life of man is ſoone cut of.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly if any of theſe foure <hi>faculties</hi> haue not his due effect, then the ſtomacke (in which is the <hi>Nutritiue appetite</hi>) doth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay: or the liueor, in which the ſubtile matter is ſeperated from
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14967:11"/>the groſſe, is defectiue: or the members to be nouriſhed, are not nouriſhed by way of the vaines, through the which humor and moiſture are conveyed: or the arteries, by which the vitall ſpirites are led. In all this it doth appeare how ſhorte the life of man is, and how ſoone it is cut of by ſickneſſe, beſides many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (almoſt innumerable) meanes, which are inſtrumentes to ſhorten his life. If then there be ſo many meanes to inda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mage and indaunger mans life, and ſo fewe to preſerue it, howe can there be any reckoning made of the length of it? but that with the Princely Prophet and Propheticall Prince King David it may be deemed to be but as a ſpanne lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g; or,<note place="margin">Pſal. 59.6. Pſal. 90.9.</note> like to a tale which is told, and ſuddainly ended; to a bubble vpon the water ſoone broken; to a miſte, which quickly vaniſheth; to a ſhippe, which ſaileth ſo ſpeedely, thaa it cannot be ſeene which way it wente; and to an arrow, or a birde flying in the aire. Many ſuch ſharpe ſimilitudes haue beene ſet downe by them, that haue duly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered the ſhortnes of mans life. And ſurely though ſome liue a little longer then other, and moſt men doe hope or at leaſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sire to liue long: yet every man doth ſee that hee which liueth longeſt, doth but borrow (as it were) a ſmall time of his fellowes, and in that little time, that he liueth longer then others, he ſtill haſteneth vnto his end: for as a man, which is in a ſhippe ſailing on the ſeas, whither he ſitte, ſtande, or walke, the ſhippe ſtill goeth on her way, and he that is in her, goeth with her: ſo man howſoever he be buſied in this worlde, whether idle or occupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, whether aſleepe or awaking, time paſſeth away, and his life in, and with time, yea even in a moment of time is cutte of. For if the longeſt liuer in the world be asked how long he eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the time, or how ſoone it is paſt ſince he was borne, hee will aunſwere it ſeemeth vnto him but as yeſterday: except it be one, whoſe life hath bene full of miſeries, to him (perchaunce) every day will ſeeme a moonth, and every moonth a yeare,<note place="margin">Pſal. 90.10.</note> and the time to longe that he hath liued, David the Prophet telleth vs that <hi>the age of man is three ſcore yeares and ten, and if hee liue anie longer, it is rather to bee reckoned a vexation, then a life:</hi> this is a ſhort time, for a man to liue no longer, and yet if every one might at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:14967:12"/>to theſe yeares, the life of man might be ſaid to be of ſome length. But if it were poſſible to record the yeares of every man that dieth, we ſhould finde in that large Regiſter of mens liues, that where one man ariueth to the age of threeſcore yeares end ten, there are a hundreth which doe not ſee halfe ſo many: there dye many moe in their infancy, then in their ripe yeares; &amp; moe in youth, then in olde age: all which ſheweth how ſhorte this life is, and what thou art in the Fruition thereof. Adde vnto this the Vncertainty thereof, wherein thou maieſt quickly conceiue how many and ſundry ſortes of caſualties thy life is ſubiect vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, which makes that more vncertaine then the winde, that is, ever mutable and full of alteration. To confirme this, if wee ſhould goe about to reckon how many inſtruments death hath to bring every mans life to an vnexpected end, the beſt memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry would rather faile to reckon vp the ſeveral engines that death vſeth to deſtroy mans life withall, then that death would want meanes to worke a ſodaine and an vncertaine end of mans life.</p>
                  <p>This may be prooved by diverſe examples of men of all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees, ſortes, and conditions, whoe in their beſt ſtrength and chiefeſt time of their health and proſperity haue bene ſuddain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet vpon by the vncertaine executioners of death, when they leaſt ſuſpected them or thought thereof.<note place="margin">Aul Ge Lib. <hi>15.</hi> Cap. <hi>20.</hi>
                     </note> As for example; The famous greeke Poet <hi>Euripides</hi> (being in good health) ſupped with <hi>Archelaus;</hi> after the which, as he returned home, when he thought himſelfe leaſt in daunger of death, he was ſodainly, and that on a trice, torne to pieces with dogges and ſo founde by tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, how vncertaine this life is.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Caeſar</hi> (who had paſt infinite perilles in the warres) was (by <hi>Brutus</hi> and <hi>Caſſius</hi>) ſlaine ſuddainly in the Senate houſe,<note place="margin">Plutarch. in vita C. Caeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris.</note> where he thought his life to be moſt ſafe, and leaſt ſuſpected the daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of death: ſo approuing (by his vntimely end) the vncertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of every mans life. <hi>Q. Curtius</hi> writting the hiſtory of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander the great,</hi> reporteth that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had conquered the world and death to, as it ſeemed to himſelfe, he was, comming to <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> caught ſuddainly by death, and made to know and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe that vncertaine is the life of man: though he were ſo great
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14967:12"/>a monarch. <hi>T. Hoſtilius,</hi> the third King of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Plutarch in vita Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mae.</note> vvhen he ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed himſelfe ſafeſt and freeſt from deathes darte, vvas ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken on the ſoddaine with a thunder bolte, and his houſe burn to aſhes with the lightening. <hi>Tarquinius Prtſcus</hi> alſo the 5. King of <hi>Rome</hi> was, ſitting at dinner, (when he leaſt dreamed of death) choaked with the boane of a fiſh, and died thereof that night: all which may well witneſſe how ſhorte, and howe vncerteine the life of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The Poets haue preatily fained that there are three ſiſters, whome <hi>Seneca</hi> called the <hi>Deſtinies,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Cic. Lib. de natura deor.</note> and <hi>Cicero</hi> ſuppoſed to be the daughters of <hi>Herebus</hi> and <hi>Nox,</hi> whome they affirme to be very much buſied about the life of man: their names are <hi>Clotho,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Clotho colu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> geſtat, Lache<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſis irahit, Atropos occai.</note> 
                     <hi>Lacheſis,</hi> and <hi>Atropos:</hi> the firſt doth weaue the threede of life, the ſecond doth lengthen it a little, and the laſt doth cleane cut it of: but the laſt of the three hath the quickeſt hande in her woorkes; for vvhat the other two doe frame for a time, that ſhe doth vndoe in the moment of time: and the threede of life, though it ſhould bee ſomewhat longe in ſpinning, yet it is cut of in the twinckling of an eie, and vvhen vve thinke it is ſtron. geſt, then commeth <hi>Atropos</hi> vnawares to perfourme and playe her parte. Death hath alſo three principall ſervauntes, vvhich he imployeth much, and often about this buſines, and they as diligently put in execution and perfourme what he commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth for the ſhortening and ſoone cutting of, of the life of man, vvhoſe names (as caſualty, infirmity, and olde age) gaue ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient proofe and teſtimony that ſhorte oftentimes, and moſt vncertaine is the life of man, &amp; what accoumpt we ſhould make of it, and what man is in the fruition thereof.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. 7.</hi> The Conſideration vvhat thou art in the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſo painfull a life.</head>
                  <p>THis Conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> concerning mans life, is of the grievous paines &amp; miſerable torments, which very often and moſt commonly do accompany thy ſelfe: as, <hi>Sicknes in thy body,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14967:13"/>Sorovves and paſſions of the minds, the Vakndneſſe of friendes, the Envie of enemies, the Deceipte of flatterers, and other vvorldely Miſhappes,</hi> vvhich breede ſuch multitudes of miſeries, as are almoſt vnpoſſible to bee named, and very harde and pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full with patience to be endured.</p>
                  <p>And firſt for the grievous paines that <hi>Sickneſſe</hi> breedeth and bringeth vnto the body, we ſee, and daily experience telleth vs, that many men are ſo tormented therewith, that their whole life from the cradle to the graue is but the drawing of an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fainting breath, and (as it were) a lingring death, or rather a painfull life, more grievous then death it ſelfe. As the fiſh <hi>Clupea</hi> (which when the moone increaſeth, is white, and when it doth decreaſe, becommeth blacke, grovving to any great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, killeth himſelfe for the paines of thoſe prickles, that come out of his owne ſides; ſo men poſſeſſed and payed with ſicknes doe chaunge both colour and complexion as <hi>Clupea</hi> doth, or as the moone waxeth and waneth: and vvhen they grovv to any yeares, the prickles of their paines is the cauſe of their death. If vve ſhoulde ſeeke for examples to ſhewe how that many men haue beene mightily tormented with ſickneſſe, vve might eaſily find &amp; ſee an endles ſea of inſtaunces to confirme this concluſion, wherein we vvill not wade much to wearie the Reader, but rather referre him to conſider of the cruell experiment that poore miſerable men doe make thereof, who pining with continuall ſickneſſe languiſh all their liues long from their mothers breaſtes till they bee borne of foure, and brought to their laſt and longe home: onely, and for a taſte herein, I will ſet before him a fevve (of many) ſuch examples as the holy ſcriptures offer vnto vs. <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Ionathan,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. Sam 4.4. Math. 9.</note> the ſonne of <hi>Saule,</hi> was lame of both his legges, and ledde a lingring languiſhing life all his daies. <hi>Iïrus</hi> daughter vvaſted vvith ſickneſſe, and the vvoman of <hi>Canaans</hi> daughter vexed with a Devill, had ended their daies vvith dolour and griefe, if <hi>CHRIST,</hi> at the humble ſuite and petition of their parentes,<note place="margin">Mar. 5.</note> had not ſhewed mercy vnto both. <hi>Marke</hi> maketh mention of a miſerable vvoman, vvhoſe body with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14967:13"/>ſickeneſſe vvas vvonderfully vveakened, and vvhoſe wealth vvith Phiſitians vvas vvaſted, her iſſue of blood continually increaſing, ſo that in twealue yeares ſhe never had eaſe one day. What what ſhall I ſpeake of that woman, whome her infirmities had bowed togeather? and of whome <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaide,<note place="margin">Luc. 13.</note> that Satan had bounde her for eighteene yeares.<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.1.</note> The poore man that laye at the poole of <hi>Betheſda</hi> keapt his bedde eight and thirty yeares not able to helpe himſelfe till <hi>Chriſt</hi> healped him. The ſame vvas the ſtate of <hi>Agbarus</hi> King of <hi>Edeſſa,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Euſeb. Lih. <hi>1.</hi> Cap. <hi>14.</hi>
                     </note> of vvhome <hi>Euſebius</hi> maketh mention: it vvere to longe, and an infinite laboure for me to lay dovvne all that might be remembred to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe: let him that would knowe more, aske the Phiſitian how many ſundry ſortes of diſeaſes he ſeemeth to knovve, though he ſeldome cureth moſt of them, all which are ordained for the puniſhment of ſinners,<note place="margin">Iob. 1.</note> and are inflicted vpon miſerable men in all ages. Onely I will ende with poore and patient <hi>Iob</hi> whoſe life during his triall was much more grievous then death, whoſe children were deſtroyed ſuddainly, whoſe, goods were taken from him violently, whoſe body was diſeaſed ſtraungly, whoſe wife vpbraided him wickedly, whoſe friends rebuked him ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; what greater Croſſe could be laid on man? bereaſt of childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">chap. 2.</note> ſpoiled of goods, abuſed by his wife, condemned by his friends, ſore in body, ſicke in mind, what miſery may be compared here with? was it any marvaile that he deſired his death,<note place="margin">Cap. 10.18.</note> or rather that he had never beene borne?</p>
                  <p>Now, how painfull the life of man is, which is ſubiect vnto ſo much ſorow, we may perceiue it by the viſage, and ſee it in the eſtate of their bodies who are overwhealmed therewith. For moſt commonly their bones are dried vp, and their bodies ther by made like vnto an anatomy: whereof grewe that olde <hi>Adage,</hi> vvhich adviſeth a man <hi>not to eate vp his hearte,</hi> ſignifying that ſuch as are troubled vvith much sorovve, conſume avvay, even as if they had eaten vp their owne heartes, and end their liues with ſupping vp that ſowre potion. Hovv pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full mans life is, that is poſſeſſed vvith ſorovve, may well bee perceiued, and that everie man hath his parte
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14967:14"/>thereof, is pregnant to be proued, for that is true which the Poet teſtifieth thereof, ſpeaking to man thus:
<q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Quocun<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> aspiceres, gemitus, luctuſ<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> ſonabant:</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Forma<expan>
                                    <am>
                                       <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                    </am>
                                    <ex>que</ex>
                                 </expan> non taciti funeris intus erat.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                     </q> that is,
<q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Which way ſo-e're thou looke about,</l>
                           <l>There ſighes and ſobbes doe ſound:</l>
                           <l>It is no ſilent burials ſhape,</l>
                           <l>That in thy ſelfe was found.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q> Theſe verſes doe well declare hovv that mans life is full fraught with cares &amp; ſorrowes. Care men haue to preuent perils as they are comming towardes them, and they ſorrow when they ſee that they cannot overcome thoſe, which are already befallen them: ſo that ſorrow ſitteth (as it were) on euery ſide, and at e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very hand, before and behinde man; whereby his life is enviro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with perpetuall paines.</p>
                  <p>And as for the paines, or deadly tormentes rather, that by meanes of externall evils (as, <hi>the vnkindneſſe of friendes, the envie of enemies,</hi> and, <hi>the deceipte of flatterers</hi>) doe inſeparably accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mans life, they are to too well knowne to euery man both in their owne particular experience, and alſo in the examples of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. For the firſt, it is moſt true, and not doubted of by any, that the greateſt calamity that can happen to a man, and may moſt grieue &amp; moleſt a faithful friend, is to be vnfaithfully dealt withall by him, whom he accompted and eſteemed for his beſt friend: this made the poore Poet thus pittifully to complaine of his friendes vnfaithfulneſſe,
<q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Omnia iam fient, fieri quae poſſe negabam,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Et nil eſt de que non ſit habenda fides:</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Hac ego vaticinor, quia ſum deceptus ab illo</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Laturum miſero quem mihirebar opem.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                     </q> that is,
<q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>All things ſhal be, which once I deem'd could ne're be done:</l>
                           <l>And nought there is, to which my faith ſhal not be wonne.</l>
                           <l>This I foretell, becauſe I was deceiu'd by him,</l>
                           <l>Who vnto me I thought would ſuccour bring.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:14967:14"/>
                  <p>By this it ſhoulde ſeeme that the poore miſerable baniſhed Poet felte nothing more grievous amiddeſt all his miſeries in his exile, then the deceipte of his reputed friende: vvhereby alſo this is made manifeſte, that greate is the griefe, and much is the paine that falſhoode in friendſhippe procureth a man.</p>
                  <p>The painefull tormente that <hi>an envious enemy</hi> worketh a man is little inferiour, nay rather it equalleth the former. For this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, ſet on rage, and inflamed vvith ire,<note place="margin">T. Liuius.</note> is reſolued (as an vnextinguiſhable fire) to conſume the life, the honour and the whole eſtate of him that is envied: and vvho is hee that is truely vertuous vvhich is not ſubiect to envies iavves?<note place="margin">Val. Max. Lib <hi>4.</hi> Tit. de amicit. Xen. in Paed. Cyri. l. i.</note> And as <hi>Xenophon</hi> ſaith, <hi>hee is in verie evill caſe whome no man envieth:</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther coulde hee in his daies remember any vertuous man that was not cruelly ſtunge vvith this poyſoned and moſt venemous ſerpent: vvhereby wee may vvell note hovve that mans life is much tormented with envie.</p>
                  <p>Laſtly, of the <hi>deceite of flatterers,</hi> hew farre forth it tormenteth mans minde, this at the firſt is not ſeene of moſt men, but ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth hidde as a padde in the ſtravve. For the flatterer cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his knavery vvith the cloake of good counſell; and ſhaddovveth his ſubtile deviſe by ſoothing and ſmoothing of him, vvhome hee is aboute to deceiue, euermore pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and commending his actions, howe euill ſoeuer; and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſing the vvorkes and deedes of others, hovve good ſoeuer; as hee findeth his humor, and may beſt feede the fantaſie of him that he followeth, vntill hee haue vvonne him to vvorke his owne woe, and in the end brought him to the deepe dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon of vtter deſtruction: then (but commonly to late) men repent them that euer they knewe ſuch companions: and are vveary of them, when they perceiue howe that they haue broughte them ſorrowe, ſhame, and confuſion, to vexe, grieue and torment their mindes continually and as long as they haue daies to liue: neither is this the leaſt adverſary, though laſt ſet downe heere, that troubleth and diſquieteth the life of man.</p>
                  <pb n="22" facs="tcp:14967:15"/>
                  <p>By theſe and ſuch other meanes, more then can vvell be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted, to mans life (fraught with anguiſh and paine) is made ſo loathſome vnto himſelfe,<note place="margin">1. Kin. 19.4.</note> that vvho is he vvhich with <hi>Elyas</hi> doth not <hi>wiſh to die,</hi> &amp; confeſſe that he is not better then his fathers: whoſe bodies be at reſt, as he vvould be? and ſaith not vvith Paule: <hi>Cupio diſſolui,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Phil. 1.23.</note> 
                     <hi>&amp; eſſe cum Chriſto,</hi> I deſire to be diſſolved and to be vvith Chriſt? For that vvere to a Chriſtian heart advantage in deed. By the rules of Chriſtianity vvee ſhould learne truely to be contented vvith all croſſes and calamities vvhich happen vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs in the courſe of this life; yet our natural corruption is ſuch, as it vvill not ſuffer vs to indure troubles vvith patience. This, that hath beene ſaid, may in ſome ſort ſuffice to ſhevv (though not fully and perfectly) hovv paineful, hovv tormenting, and hovv ful of cares the courſe of this life is: &amp; ſerveth fitly to ſtirre and mooue thee to conſider and vveigh vvell vvith thy ſelfe vvhat thou art in enioying of ſo ſhort, ſo vncertaine, &amp; ſo paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a life, as this is.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. 8.</hi> The Conſideration what thou arte in thy death, and manner of dying.</head>
                  <p>THe laſt Conſideration of this firſt part, is; concerning thy <hi>death:</hi> vve meane not here to diſcourſe, but curſorilie, of the difference betvveene <hi>corporall</hi> and <hi>spirituall, temporall</hi> and <hi>eternall</hi> death, beſt beſeeming the pens and paines of great and graue Divines, but only to ſpeake of the death of the body moſt familiar and beſt knowne to all men. It is an old ſaying &amp; very true: that <hi>as ſure as man is borne, ſo ſure he is to die.</hi> Some ſaid that death is three folde, but rather might haue ſaid, and that more ſoundly, and more truely, that it hath three degrees: the firſt <hi>Naturall,</hi> the ſecond <hi>Criminall,</hi> the thirde <hi>Iudiciall.</hi> For the firſt, vvhich is <hi>Naturall</hi> or the diſſolution of nature, this (as is ſaid before) as it is common to all men, and no man is exempted from it, ſo it hath in it many things ſeeming very fearefull, and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14967:15"/>procuring much amazement, vvhich yet ought not to bee fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at all: as vvhen death dravveth neere (ſending before him his habinger <hi>Sicknes</hi>) he preſenteth vnto the ſicke man a gaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full countenance, and leane bones vvithout fleſh: yea hee doth offer to his remembraunce the loſſe of all his goods and honors, his departure from his friendes, the ſequeſtring of his ſoule from his body, and the ſeperating of himſelfe from the vvorld &amp; from all things in the vvorld, hovv deare and delightfull ſoeuer vnto him: vvhereby the ſenſes are all over-loaden and burthened vvith ſorrovv; according to the ſaying of the Poet:
<q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Mille modis lethi miſeros mors vnafatigat.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                     </q> that is,
<q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>A thouſand kindes of deathes and moe,</l>
                           <l>Death hath at hand, to vvorke mansvvoe.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q> All vvhich, behelde of the meere naturall man in the grimme viſage of death (as it vvere in a looking glaſſe) ſeeme very dread full; but of theſe chiefely, the loue of this life maketh him moſt of all to feare death, and yet to him that is truly vviſe the ſadde ſight of death yeeldeth no ſuch hideous aſpect or diſcontent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but rather mooueth him to remember and make good vſe of that excellent ſaying of <hi>Seneca:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Sen. epiſt. <hi>62.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Before olde age I had care to liue vvell, that I might in olde age die well,</hi> that is vvillingly. For to die vvillingly, is to die vvell: vvhich if a man vvould conſider and put in practiſe, then needed he not to feare this naturall death of the body. Full vvell ſaid the Heathen Philoſopher,<note place="margin">Cice. in ſom Scip.</note> that vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe God ſhould free man from the keepers (or from that pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) of the body, there could be no paſſage into heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Though death doe diſſolue this temporall and momentary life fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dy; yet if a good death follow a good life, it addeth a longer life vnto this temporall and tranſitory life, and it taketh away all cares and calamities from the body and life of man, in ſo much that ſuch a death may aptly be called the end of labours, the conſervation of victory, the gates of life, and the entraunce into euerlaſting felicity. Thus may the vertuous, diſcreete, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate man learne to know what he is concerning the firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of death, vvhich we cal <hi>naturall,</hi> or the diſſolution of nature.
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14967:16"/>As touching the ſecond degree of death, vvhich vvee call <hi>Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minall,</hi> or the death of offence, this vnto many men ſeemeth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing fearfull, although it ought more to bee feared then the firſt. The firſt degree of <hi>Naturall</hi> death every man muſt yeelde vnto, and paye vndoubtedly as a due debte to Nature, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the Creator of Natures vvorkes: but the ſeconde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of death, vvhich is the death of <hi>offence,</hi> as it begonne and brought in that firſt death vvhich vvee tearme <hi>Naturall;</hi> ſo is it, or it ought to be much more feared then the ſame. For one of the Fathers ſaith,<note place="margin">Aug. ſup. Gen.</note> that <hi>Adam and Eue beganne to dye in the ſame day that they did receiue the lavve of death;</hi> that is vvhen they offended firſt, and that by one mans offence, death came vnto all men. This death of offence vvhich is cauſe firſt of the <hi>Naturall,</hi> then of the <hi>Iudiciall</hi> death, ought there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore moſt of all to be feared; yet wee ſee, and that to to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly, hovve men make ſmall reckoning of this death and doe leaſt dreade it, elſe vvoulde they not be ſo proane and ready to runne on head-long, and to committe thoſe offences, that doe procure death, and perpetuall deſtruction. This <hi>death of offence,</hi> or the offence it ſelfe, vvhich cauſeth death, ought to be very much feared. For though men, while they liue, doe lightly and little regard it; yet it bringeth with it to torment them (vvhen they are a dying) ſhame horrour and confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The laſt degree of death,or the laſt effect of it, is the death of <hi>Iudgment:</hi> this hath three ſtepps or ſtaires by which it mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth either to eternal happines, or elſe deſcendeth vnto endleſſe paines and torments. For Iudgment is ſaide to be of three ſortes:<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> the firſt is <hi>of our ſelues;</hi>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the ſeconde is <hi>of men;</hi>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and the third is of, or, <hi>by the Creator of man.</hi> For the firſt Iudgment <hi>of our ſelues</hi> concerning our deathes and of our deſertes of death, this is <hi>invvarde</hi> and contained in the Conſcience of everie man, vvhich Conſcience vvhen it giueth iudgment againſt a man, it makes him feele the paines of death in life, and it figu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vnto him the perpetuall paines vvhich he ſhall endure after death.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14967:16"/>An heathen Philoſopher could ſay that <hi>a guilty conſcience is like to an vlcer in the body.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Plut de animi tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillitate.</note> For it leaueth ſorrowe and griefe wounding him and feaſtering in his heart and minde continually. When reaſon can relieue the minde moued otherwiſe to ſadneſſe, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing can eaſe the galling and torture of a guilty Conſcience;<note place="margin">Ovid lib <hi>1.</hi> de Ponto Eleg. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> which cauſed the comfortleſſe Poet to confeſſe and ſay:
<q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Paenitet, o ſi quid miſerorum creditur vlli,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Paenitet, et facto torqueor ipſe meo.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                     </q> that is,
<q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>I doe repent, if any wretched wight,</l>
                           <l>Might credit haue, or be beleud in this:</l>
                           <l>It grieveth me, and galleth day and night</l>
                           <l>My woefull hearte, that I haue done amiſſe.</l>
                           <l>This is the fruite, and onely eaſe I finde,</l>
                           <l>A guilty deede, yealde to a galled minde.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q> Therefore this Iudgment of our ſelues in our owne conſciences, that we haue not onely deſerued this temporall but an eternall death, is (without it be eaſed by perfect Penitence) a double death vnto vs.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond ſteppe of ludgment, is the Iudgement <hi>of men:</hi> whereon death alſo doth depend. As the iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of our ſelues is <hi>internall,</hi> and in our owne conſciences: ſo the iudgment of men is <hi>externall,</hi> depending vpon exteriour proofes &amp; probabilities, whereby they giue their iudgment of life and death. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though that the iudgment of men, be not alvvaies true in their difinitiue ſentence, and decree of men, howe they haue deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved either to liue or dye; becauſe that they which are the ludges, whither with authority or without, may miſtake the lawes by the which they iudge: or elſe thoſe, that produce proofes vnto them, may either wilfully or ignorantly miſinforme and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guide them: yet it behoueth every wiſe man diſcreetly to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte himſelfe vnto that ſentence of the Law, which limitteth vnto him either life or death.<note place="margin">Demosth. Con And</note> For as the excellent Orator affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, <hi>it is not lawfull to maligne magiſtrates though they be wicked &amp; evill:</hi> the reaſon thereof is, becauſe that they, vvhen they do giue iudgment of life and death, are the ſubſtitutes of him,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:14967:17"/>vvho is the author of life and death. And, if thou vvilt dye vvell, avoide and eſchevve all evill deedes, vvhich are the occaſions of this iudgement of men, vvhich deeme and iudge thee worthy of death. For this iudgment of death doth com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly follow the evill actions of a badde life.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The laſt ſteppe, in the laſt degree of death, vvhich is called <hi>the finall Iudgment,</hi> followeth death, at the latter daic, vvhen the vniverſall iudgment of mankinde ſhall bee, and either eternall life or eternall death inſueth. Of this I pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to ſpeake but as an occurrent by the vvay. Then ſhall bee the beginning of glory to the good, and to the vvic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked of ſhame and confuſion: then ſhall bee the ſeperation of the ſheepe from the goates, of the corne from the cockle; and of the bleſſed from the accurſed. After this, then they, that receiue the ſentence of life, ſhall never dye or feare death any more: and thoſe, vvhich are appointed to dye, can never hope for life againe: whatſoever ſome men haue dreamed of this matter, whereof we purpoſe not heere to intreate. This laſt degree of death, or difference betweene life and death, hath in it either much <hi>feare</hi> or much <hi>ioy:</hi> feare to the wicked in reſpect of former offences, but ioy vnto the faithfull in their hope of enioying future happineſſe, which followeth after a vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous life and a godly end.<note place="margin">Lactan. in divinis inſt. Lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>4</hi>
                     </note> And as <hi>Lactantius</hi> alleadgeth: <hi>if it be asked of vs, vvhyther death bee good or evill, vvee muſt aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſvvere, that this or that mans death is good or bad, as his life was either good or bad vvhich hee had lead before.</hi> For if thy life be good, then vvill thy death alſo be good vnto thee: but if thy life be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, then likewiſe is death evill vnto thee.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="conclustion" type="chapter">
                  <head>The Concluſion of this firſt parte of the firſt pointe of Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion concerning thy ſelfe, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hat then arte.</head>
                  <p>BY this litle touch or light handling of Conſideration, herein (gentle Reader) tendered vnto thee, (if thou haſt read over the ſame with good regarde) thou maieſt thereby make ſome triall concerning the knovvledge of thy ſelfe, what thou
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:14967:17"/>arte in thy Creation, in thy Procreation and byr the, in thy Life, and in thy Death. All which, if thou doe well and adviſedly conſider, thou ſhalt finde that to be true,<note place="margin">Bernardus. in ſenten</note> which <hi>Bernard</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, that man is ſicke of a threefolde malady; in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, in the middle, and in the ending; that is, in his <hi>birth,</hi> in his <hi>life,</hi> and in his <hi>death.</hi> For his birth is <hi>vnpure,</hi> his life is <hi>perverſe,</hi> &amp; his death <hi>daungerous.</hi> His birth it is <hi>vnpure,</hi> by reaſon of our firſt parents fall, and the daily offences of our naturall parents,<note place="margin">Pſal. 51.5.</note> which mooued the Pſalmiſt (well weighing it) to ſay that <hi>in ſinne hee vvas conceiued.</hi> His life is <hi>perverſe,</hi> becauſe that by nature he is proane to all evill actions. His death is <hi>daungerous,</hi> becauſe his life is vitious. There is in our birthe, <hi>a beginning</hi> of ſorrowe: there is in our liues, <hi>a continuance</hi> of the ſame: &amp; there is in our deathes, either <hi>a diſſolution,</hi> or elſe <hi>a perpetuall poſſeſſion</hi> thereof.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The end of the firſt Section of the firſt parte of Conſideration.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:14967:18"/>
               <head>The Conſideration <hi>THE SECOND SECTION OF</hi> the firſt part of the Conſideration of humane Condition.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. 1.</hi> The Conſideration of thy ſelfe, who thou art.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Ow having ſaid ſomewhat concerning the firſt part of the firſt point of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of thy ſelfe, which is, <hi>What thou art:</hi> it is neceſſary that we proceed. farther to the ſeconde part of this firſt point of Conſideration; which is, <hi>Who thou art.</hi> The Conſideration whereof doth containe in it the remembrance &amp; reknowledgement of thy parentage, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, and deſcent: the knowledge of thy ſtate of body, of thy vvealth, calling, dignity and wiſedome. To the goodneſſe and greatneſſe of which giftes the Philoſophers in former times haue attribured a great part of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s felicity; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> calling Riches, Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, &amp; Honors, the goods of <hi>fortune;</hi>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Health, Stre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth &amp; Beauty, they tearmed the goods of the <hi>body;</hi>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Wiſedome, Learning and Vertue they eſteemed to be the goods of the <hi>Minde.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By the true Conſideration of thy ſelfe, <hi>vvho thou art in the poſſeſſion of theſe bleſſings,</hi> thou maieſt learne to know, that if thou haue any, or all of them, thou art yet no otherwiſe happy in them, then according as thou doeſt vſe them: for if it be true, that there is a difference betweene <hi>vſing</hi> and <hi>enjoying</hi> of thinges; in that wee are ſaide properly to <hi>vſe</hi> onely thoſe thinges that are temporall;<note place="margin">Pet. Lumb. Lib. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> and to <hi>emote</hi> thoſe thinges that are eternall: thou maieſt conſider that thy parentage, thy health, thy digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, &amp; thy wiſdome being things te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral &amp; tranſitory, are then only to be vſed of thee here for a time, &amp; that but for very ſhort time; for thou maiſt by no means enioy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alwaies. This, wel po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered &amp; thought vpon, will ſoone bring thee to the knowledge
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14967:18"/>of thy ſelfe, <hi>Who thou art.</hi> For there is nothing that letteth and hindereth a man more from the knowledge of himſelfe, then the opinion and fonde conceipte he hath of the goodnes, great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and durableneſſe of thoſe worldly bleſſings, which he doth poſſeſſe, and ſo entirely affect. Therefore to vveede out the over-weening opinion thereof, vvee vvill firſt beginne with thy linage and parentage, and ſo bring thee by little and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle into the conſideration of thy ſelfe, <hi>vvho thou art.</hi> Art thou deſcended of a noble family, or of a baſe linage? if thou be noble borne, then commonly <hi>pride</hi> and <hi>preſumption</hi> catch holde and lay ſuch violent handes on thy vvill, thy affection, and thy vnderſtanding, that they can hardlie bee remooued from thee, till they haue remooued thee from the knowledge of thy ſelfe, <hi>who thou art.</hi> For thy preſumptuous pride and ſelfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liking affection will make thee beleeue that thou art much better, then indeed thou art. This makes men many times to meaſure their owne greatnes of birth as they doe their ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, vvhich alwaies ſeeme bigger then their bodies, and by degree it draweth them to beleeue that their birth and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentages are farre better then the birthes and parentages of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others are, or may be.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Q. Curt.</note>As, <hi>Alexander</hi> the great, after he had obtained many &amp; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table victories, could not then be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented to be called any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger the ſonne of <hi>Philip</hi> King of <hi>Macedon,</hi> but vvould needs bee accompted the ſonne of <hi>Iupiter Hammon,</hi> and ſo be dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to haue beene deſcended from the Gods. <hi>Sabor</hi> King of <hi>Perſia</hi> called himſelfe <hi>King of Kings, partaker of the planets,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Herodotus Lib. <hi>2. H</hi>
                     </note> and, <hi>brother to the Sunne and Moone. Hanno</hi> the <hi>Carthaginian</hi> cauſed birdes to bee taken, and taught to ſay, <hi>Hanno is a God:</hi> which birdes were afterwarde caſt abroade in diverſe places, that they might publiſh this his feined Deitie vnto the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
                  <p>Even ſo commonly wee ſee that many of noble birthe and greate parentage perſvvade themſelues that they exceede all others in eſtimation of bloode and linage: vvhereas they mighte conſider vvith themſelues that howe noblye ſoeuer
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14967:19"/>they are borne, their Nobility hath a beginning, not by their own, but by their Aunceſtors deſerts &amp; vertues; wherfore if that there be not in them good partes and properties aunſwereable to the behaviour and good qualities of their Elders, and their owne birthes, then are they but a blemiſh to their Elders, and a ſtaine to their names, and honors. VVe ſee the faireſt and rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſilkes, when once they receiue any blemiſh or ſtaine, they are more disfigured and in greater diſgrace then cloath, or other matter of leſſe moment and reckoning: even ſo is it in the eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Nobility. For a fault in a man of great birth and paren<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tage is more noted, and breedeth vnto him greater diſgrace and diſhonour, then the ſame ſhould do vnto a man of leſſe and low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er dignity. It is not inough to be borne of high bloude, without vertue aunſwerable to that birth: neither with reaſon may a noble man, becauſe he is honourably deſcended, challendge loue, eſtimation, and honour of the actions accompliſhed by his Aunceſtors, vnleſſe his owne carriage be correſpondent &amp; aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to theirs,<note place="margin">Sen. in Here. fur.</note> and to his owne calling: for <hi>Seneca</hi> ſayeth, &amp; that very truely, that, <hi>bee vvhich braggeth of his kindred, commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth that which concerneth others.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ovid. lib. <hi>13.</hi> Meta.</note> And the Poet ſpeaking to the ſame purpoſe ſaide very well.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Nam genus, et proaves, et quae non fecimus ipſi,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ix ea noſtra voco.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>that is.</l>
                     <l>What kindred did, or Elders ours,</l>
                     <l>And what we haue not donne,</l>
                     <l>I call not ours:it ſcarcely hath</l>
                     <l>Vs any credit wonne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>This cauſed a Gentle man of great worth and worthines,<note place="margin">S. Philip Sidney.</note> as any that hath liued in our age, to adde this mote vnderneath his coate of armes: <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ix ea noſtra voco.</hi> VVho although hee might moſt deſeruedly haue claimed vnto himſelfe as much honor as ever any of his Aunceſtors haue had, yet he would not appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate their vertues (which could not be called his) vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: for he had rather gaine glory by his owne noble and wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy actes, then be accoumpted renowmed for the greatnes of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14967:19"/>his Aunceſtors, how neere and how deere ſoever vnto him. As his noble minde is worthy of memory in all ages, and his heroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call actes never to be committed to oblivion: ſo are they (which degenerate from their Elders, or doe diſgrace and diſhonor the honourable actions of their Aunceſtors) to be accoumpted wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy (if not of all ſhame) yet of a place in <hi>Lethes</hi> lake to lye in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually. <hi>Q. Pompeius</hi> Pretor of <hi>Rome</hi> did moſt ſtoutely and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly carry himſelfe, when he did interdict and diſhinherite the ſonne of <hi>Q. Fabius Max.</hi> from the vſe and benefit of all his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers goods, becauſe he did degenerate from the vertues of his noble father, and ſpent that moſt luxuriouſly, which his father had moſt honorably gotten. There was a law amongſt the <hi>Rhodians,</hi> that what ſonne ſoever followed not the foot-ſteps of their fathers vertues ſhould be diſhinherited: which lawe if it were kept, &amp; did continue in force amongſt vs this day, it would make many a ſonne goe without goods, and leaue his fathers liuing for others to inherite. For out daies make experience of that, which the Poet ſpake, and applied to former ages.</p>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Aequat rara patrem ſoboles,<note place="margin">Honter.</note> ſed plurimi ab illis</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Degenerant, pauci ſuperant probitate parentem.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Odyſſ. <hi>1</hi>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                     <l>that is,</l>
                     <l>Fewe ſonnes are found of fathers mindes,</l>
                     <l>Or equall them in vertues actes:</l>
                     <l>The greateſt ſorte growe out of kinde;</l>
                     <l>Who doth regard his fathers factes?</l>
                     <l>Children ſeldome ſeeke indeede,</l>
                     <l>Their ſires (in goodneſſe) to exceede.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <p>Now againe on the other ſide, if thy birth and parentage bee meane, then moſt commonly art thou drawen to deſpaire of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any great advaunceme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, although thou doe deſerue it wel: for Envy alwaies followeth Vertue, and that moſt of all, when it is placed in one of meane Parentage. For vſually thoſe, that hold themſelues better in birth, will contemne and envy their inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours in bloud, although they bee farre theyr ſuperiours in ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and deſearte. But this ſhoulde not diſmaye him that deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth well, to expect the rewarde of his deſertes, how meane ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14967:20"/>ever his birth be. For we finde it in experience true, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples are infinite, how men, whoſe parentes vvere meane and poore, haue (for good partes in them) bene preferred to very high and great dignity. As <hi>David,</hi> a ſhepheard, yet after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes annoynted King of Iſrael.<note place="margin">Pſal. 78.</note> 
                     <hi>Tamberlane</hi> the ſon of a poore ſhephearde in <hi>Scythia,</hi> and, as ſome ſay, a ſhephearde him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, by his valoure and proweſſe became King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> and was a very mighty Monarch. The father of <hi>Sforce</hi> Duke of <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laine</hi> was a poore man, who liued by husbandrie in <hi>Catiniola,</hi> a ſmall towne or village ſituate neere vnto <hi>Ravenna:</hi> and yet his ſonne for his worth and worthynes ſo highly advaunced to ſo great a dignity. Many examples might be brought to the ſame purpoſe, of ſuch as in former times, yea and in this latter &amp; more vngratefull age of the world haue gotten by their vertues great preferments &amp; high advauncements, though their births haue bene but very baſe: of whome we omitte further to ſpeake, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we purpoſe not to diſgrace or offend any, but rather to commend vertue, and to wiſh the advauncement thereof in al. Yet by the way of advice we could wiſh ſuch as be of meane pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentage, &amp; ſo preferred to high places, to beware of al ſwelling conceipte of pride, which to to often hath infected many.</p>
                  <p>And ſo if the noble borne haue care of his cariage, &amp; avoide preſumption in the eſtimation of his honourable deſcent: &amp; the meane man ſhun diſpaire or doubt of obteining advauncement by reaſon of his birth, and to lofty a conceipt in his proſperous eſtate, then ſhall either of them conſider well and wiſely who, and what he is in his deſcent, and by his parentage.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> The Conſideration of thy ſelfe, vvho thou arte in the ſtate of thy body.</head>
                  <p>THE next Conſideration is of thy ſelfe <hi>vvho thou arte in the ſtate of thy bodie:</hi> wherein conſiſteth the eſtimation of thy health, of thy ſtrength and of thy beauty: in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:14967:20"/>whereof thou ſhalt finde who thou arte in poſſeſſing health or ſickneſſe, ſtrength or weaknes, beauty or deformity, wherein if Nature hath beſtovved on thee her giftes liberally and friendlie, ſhee giveth thee no better gifte then the Poets faine that <hi>Paris</hi> gaue to <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus,</hi> or the revvarde that hee received of her againe. For vvhen ſhee ſtroue with <hi>Iuno</hi> and <hi>Pallas</hi> for the golden ball, vvhich was to be given to her whom <hi>Paris</hi> deemed faireſt of the three; <hi>Paris</hi> beſtowed the ball on <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enus,</hi> and vvith al continuall contention with the other twaine: and ſhe rewarded him againe with <hi>Helen</hi> which was his vtter confuſion. This fable was not deviſed without very good ſignification and a certaine morall or meaning, vvhat mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtations many times follovve the friendly courſe of Nature in them, that are healthy, ſtrong, and beautifull in body. For if thou haſt thy health, then thou art commonly careleſſe of thy diet, and ſo falleſt oft to ſurfette, or elſe to vſe ſome ſuch exerciſe. as may indaunger thy health. For hee that doubteth not of his health, dare eate of manie diſhes, and (as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith) <hi>eating of many meates bringes many diſeaſes:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Sen. ad Luc. Ep. <hi>99</hi> Jd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m, Rhet. <hi>10.</hi>
                     </note> and in an an other place, <hi>vvhatſoever</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>birdes doe flie, or fiſhes ſvvimme, or beaſtes doe runne, they are buried in our bellies. If thou aske</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>vvhy vvee dye ſo ſuddainely? it is becauſe vvee liue by the death of ſo many creatures:</hi> and they that haue moſt ſtrength, are moſt boldeſt to devoure moſt creatures, whereby moſt commonly they abate their health, and conſume that vvhich they woulde faineſt pamper and feede, even their bodies. The exerciſes alſo, vvhich ſtrong bodyed men are moſt giuen vnto, doe withdraw many times to to many of ſuch, from the better exerciſes of the minde. For ſeldome is it ſeene, that men of much might are much giuen to the ſtudy of liberal ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces, or the meditation of divine things: which moued <hi>Xenocrates</hi> to exhort men that they ſhould not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe the body much without the minde, nor the minde alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether without the body; for the firſt beſt beſeemeth wraſtlers and ſuch rude people; the ſecond belongeth vnto Idle perſons; the firſt breedeth ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; ſturdy ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce; the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d begetteth
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:14967:21"/>ſtudious dulneſſe: but they that are apt and fit for beſt things, are indifferently exerciſed in both body and minde. For thoſe men, that haue ſtronge bodies, for the moſt part haue weake mindes, becauſe they ſo much exerciſe the ſtrength of their bodyes, that they ſeldome or never regarde the ſtudy of the minde:<note place="margin">Sen. ep. <hi>81.</hi>
                     </note> hovve vveake, ſayeth <hi>Seneca,</hi> are they in minde, vvhoſe ſtrength of body vvee doe much marvaile at? ſo that naturall ſtrength draweth on vnnaturall effectes, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes of thinges moſt to bee deſired to bee in men. If thou haue alſo beauty and comelineſſe of body, this bleſſing eft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoones maketh thee in the enioying thereof many times miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and infortunate. For it maketh provvde ſuch as enioy it, and provoketh others to vnlawfull luſtes and vvicked deſires, coveting the accompliſhment of their fleſhly appetites, and ſenſuall pleaſures, through the abuſe of others beauty, which is the nouriſher and procurer of pride, as the Poet telleth thee, when he ſaith:</p>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Faſtus ineſt pulchris,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ovid faſt. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>ſequitur<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> ſuperbia formam.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>which is,</l>
                  <l>Diſdaine doth dwell in beauties bowre,</l>
                  <l>And pride with beauty hath great powre.</l>
                  <p>It is to often tryed, that they, vvhich are by nature beautiful, make their external beauty of the body to be the betraier of the inwarde beauty of the minde: vvhereby vve ſee what inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niences doe follovve the health, ſtrength, and beauty of the body.</p>
                  <p>Novv contraryvviſe, if thou art either naturally ſubiect to ſickneſſe, or accidentally weake; if thou art by nature, or by caſualty deformed, vvhat anguiſh, griefe, and tormentes of minde theſe defectes and blemiſhes doe bring vvith them, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one either feeleth and findeth in himſelfe, or at the leaſt may ſee and perceiue it in others. Therefore to temper thoſe intemperate affections, which vſually abounde in ſuch as abuſe the bleſſings of the body: and alſo to avoide the inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, which doe purſue the vvants of thoſe naturall bleſſings of the body, thou oughteſt to conſſider, that if the Creator of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:14967:21"/>natures vvroks hath beſtowed the bleſſinges of health, ſtrength, and beauty vppon thee, that hee beſtowed not them to that ende vpon thee, that thou ſhouldeſt grovv provvde of them, or abuſe thy body, or deviſe hovve to make others enamored vvith thy beauty, and the rather for it vnlavvfully to deſire thee. For thou haſte receiued theſe ſvveete bleſſings to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ende: euen that to the ableneſſe of thy body thou ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ioine the vvillingnes of thy minde, to doe thoſe comely and commendable deedes, vvhich doe beautifie both the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and the minde, and vvhich laſt longer then the ſoone-fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding bloſſomes of beauty, the vveake and ever-ſlyding ſtaffe of ſtrength, and then thy health, vvhich is more vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine then all the reſt; for it is ſoone impaired and very quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly brought to vtter decaye. If then thy beauty fade, thy ſtrength faile, and thy health conſume and weare away; diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>may not thy ſelfe, but rather bee armed vvith patience. For as long as the minde is indued vvith reaſon, and good reſolution, no ſickneſſe or afflictions can bring the body ſo vveake, or ſo out of ſhape, but that a minde prepared vvith patience and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by vertue may very vvell indure. Infirmities may bee a meane to ſubdue, or at leaſt to mooue vs to ſuſtaine ſtoutly all diſlikes and diſcontentmentes of ſuch defects and effects in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. VVhich Conſideration (vvith the circumſtaunces of the ſame) concerning thy health and ſickneſſe, thy ſtrength and vveakeneſſe, thy beauty and deformity if thou beare al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvaies in thy minde, and make good vſe thereof, thou ſhalt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of thy ſelfe aright, and ſoone knovve <hi>what, and who thou arte in the ſtate of thy body.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> The Conſideration of thy ſelfe vvhat, and vvho thou art in the ſtate of thy vvealth and riches.</head>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:14967:22"/>
                  <p>THe Conſideration of thy vvealth &amp; riches doth containe two circumſtaunces to be conceived of thee, and to be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried continually in thy remembrance. The firſt is of thy wealth and poſſeſſions, hovve thou haſte gotten them: the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conde is, hovv thou doeſt vſe them. For by theſe two courſes of getting &amp; vſing thy wealth &amp; goods, they are made either good or evill vnto thee. Sometimes men doe get their goods vvell, by honeſt and lavvfull meanes, yet may they vſe them evill: but they doe ſeldome, or almoſt neuer, that get their goods by evill meanes, turne their goods ſo gotten vnto good vſes.</p>
                  <p>Now firſt, for the obtaining and getting of riches vvhither it be by lawful, or by vnlawfull meanes: it is to be conſidered that if thou haſte riches, landes, or any kinde of liuelyhood, thou haſt either gotten it by inheritance, by gift, or by thine owne indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry. If thy goods and poſſeſſions come vnto thee by inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taunce, and that thou haſte ſufficient by thine aunceſtors to mainetaine thy eſtate, then, the more thou haſt the leſſe ſhoulde bee thy care and toyle in travailing to augment thine aboundaunce, ſeeing that by inheritaunce thou haſte ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to ſuſtaine neceſsity, and to mainetaine thy calling: and yet this competency ſhoulde not breede a careleſneſſe in thee to preſerue that vnto thy poſterity, vvhich thy prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours carefully procured for thee. But ſuch commonly is the condition of mans nature, that hee alvvaies doeth deſire an alteration of his eſtate, vvhich maketh him, that hath greate poſſeſsions left him by his parentes (not knowing or conſidering vvhat paines they vſed in the obtaining of it) to bee careleſſe hovve hee conſumeth it: hee having no expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience hovve hardly it vvas had at the firſt, foreſeeth not hovve vneaſily it is recovered vvhen it is gone, or vvhat the lacke and loſſe of it is, vvhen it is miſpent. VVe ſee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times that a prodigall ſonne ſucceedeth a miſerable father: vvho, vvhen hee commeth to plenty (not by his ovvne, but by his parentes induſtrie) neuer ceaſeth to ſeeke meane, to ſpende that vvhich others haue gotten for him, being drawne by delighte to laviſh in expences, vvith a vaine opinion of
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:14967:22"/>getting fame, and procuring friendes, or other prefermentes by his liberalitie, as hee thinketh; but more truelie by his prodigalitie, as others doe thinke, and as himſelfe ſhall finde vvhen all is gone, and vvhen it is to late to grovve thriftie. The reaſon of this is, that thinges vvhich are hardly had, are ſought vvith greateſt deſire, and kepte vvith greateſt care: and on the contrary ſide, vve commonly ſee that when vvealth or almoſt any other vvorldly benefite is beſtowed on men freely, or that they obtaine it vvithout any great labour or difficultie, they then leaſt eſteeme it, and are ſooneſt vvonne to departe from it. Therefore to ſhunne both theſe extremities of prodigality, and miſery, in adminiſtring and beſtowing of thy goods and poſſeſsions, vvhich come to thee by inheritance, vſe this mediocrity, that plenty make thee not prodigall, nor poverty cauſe thee to be miſerable: the meane in this, as in other thinges (though it be harde to attaine vnto) is the ſafeſt and the profitableſt courſe, when it may be compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and well kept: as the Poet ſaith.</p>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>
                           <note place="margin">Horat lib. <hi>1.</hi> ſerm. ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>. <hi>1.</hi>
                           </note> 
                           <hi>Eſt modus in rebus, ſunt eerti deni<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> fines,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Quos vltra citra<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> nequit conſiſtere rectum.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
                  <p>which is,</p>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <l>There is a golden meane in things,</l>
                        <l>And certaine boundes are pight.</l>
                        <l>Beyonde, beſide, or ſhort of which</l>
                        <l>Cannot conſiſt the Right.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
                  <p>Then if a man grovv to wealth, or great living by other mens gifts, ſuch as were not his parents, or from whom he coulde not expect the ſame as an hereditary right; which happeneth diverſe times vnlooked for to many: wealth ſo obtained, worketh like effect as that doth, which is had by inheritaunce; that is, it maketh him that commeth ſo ſodainely and vvith ſo ſmall travaile to his aboundaunce, to take the leſſe care in kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of it, or in ſpending it vvell; for ſuch a one commonly wil verifie the old proverbe, which ſaith, <hi>light come, light go:</hi> So did <hi>Caius Caligula,</hi> who conſumed great treaſures gathered togither
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:14967:23"/>by <hi>Tiberius</hi> the Emperour. For it is reported of him, that he ſpent ſeave<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>-ſcore thouſand <hi>Seſtertia</hi> in one yeare. So did <hi>Cleopatra</hi> the laſt Queene of Aegypt, who at a ſupper, which ſhe made to <hi>M. Antonius,</hi> putting an excellent pearle into tarte vineger, wherein being reſolued, dranke it, being eſteemed at <hi>Centies Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteria</hi> which is of our money 50000.<hi rend="sup">li</hi>.</p>
                  <p>Many ſuch we haue in theſe our daies bearing the like prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall mindes, though they haue not the like meanes and abilitie: who are as ready to ſpend all their wealth, whither by gifte or by inheritance, yea and that as vainely as <hi>Heliogabalus,</hi> by wearing of precious ſtones in their ſhoes: or as <hi>Caeſar</hi> the ſonne of Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixt, who ſpent every day two hundred crownes in banquetting, maintained a multitude of paraſites, whome he fed and apparelled on his owne proper coſt, and keapt in pay eight thouſand ſouldiers continually: all which prodigally and vamely he ſpent and conſumed during his fathers daies. Haue not diverſe heires, and ſuch as haue large legacies in our daies, ſpente as laviſhly what they had, as their parents gotte the ſame wickedly? to whome may well be applied what the Poet writte of <hi>Canna,</hi> ſaying vnto him thus:
<q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <note place="margin">Mart. epig. lib. <hi>9.</hi>
                              </note>
                              <hi>Nam tu</hi> (<hi>dum metuis, ne quid poſt fatarelinquas</hi>)</l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Hauſiſti patrias luxurioſus opes.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                     </q> which is
<q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Thou haſt conſum'de thy fathers wealth,</l>
                           <l>To feede thy luſtfull minde:</l>
                           <l>For feare leaſt thou ſhouldſt after death,</l>
                           <l>Leaue ought of it behinde.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now touching the getting and ſpending of thoſe poſſeſſions, which doe accrue vnto thee by thine owne paines and induſtry: the goods ſo gotten, as they are obtained by thine owne inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, ſo <hi>Deſire</hi> was the mother, <hi>Paines</hi> the father, and <hi>Care</hi> the nurſe of the new-borne babe, <hi>Wealth:</hi> which many times maketh ſuch as brought forth and nouriſhed ſo vnnaturall a childe, like vnto the viper, which with the birth of her owne younge ones, is alwaies bereaved of her owne life. Therfore in the getting and vſing of thy riches and wealth remember theſe rules, that the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:14967:23"/>goods, which are evill gotten, doe not bring ſo much preſent profitte, pleaſure, and proſperity, as they doe cauſe future daun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,<note place="margin">Ambr. ſup. Luc. Lib. <hi>8.</hi>
                     </note> and yet the fault is not in the wealth, but in them, that haue wrongfully gotten it, or in them, that cannot vſe their wealth well. For that is true, which one ſaith,<note place="margin">Oſorius.</note> that <hi>by how much the more any thing is in his owne nature excellent, by ſo much the more is the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe therof pernicious and daungerous.</hi> So it is not the lawful vſe, but the vnlawfull abuſe of riches &amp; wealth, that is alwaies condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. Neither are the opinions of <hi>Crates, Antiſthenes,</hi> and other Philoſophers of their iudgment, good and to be followed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, who would not haue any wealth (but gaue away their goods) thinking that they would be hinderances to their deſired hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines: wherein they were deceiued, ſeeing that riches in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues are neither good nor evill, but become ſuch, as they are vſed: good to the good, and badde to the evill and wicked:<note place="margin">Ambr, vt Sup.</note> to the good they are good helpes to vertue and to vertuous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions: to the badde they are goades to pricke forwarde, and ſupporters to mainetaine all evill and vvicked actions: they make not a man the better that hath them, except they be well vſed, more <hi>then a golden bitte makes a horſe the better that beareth it:</hi> and to vſe them well is to enioy them: as to vſe them evil, is to abuſe them. The good or evill vſe of them alſo conſiſteth in the <hi>eſtimation</hi> that we make of the ſame. For if we growe once into to great a liking and loue of our goods, then they ſteale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the heart of him, that hath them, and make him a ſlaue to his owne ſubſtaunce, according to that which the Poet ſaith:
<q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <note place="margin">Ovid. fact. <hi>1</hi>
                              </note>
                              <hi>Creverunt et opes, et opum furioſa cupido,</hi>
                           </l>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Et cum poſſideant plurima, plura petunt.</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                     </q> That is,
<q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>As riches doth increaſe with men,</l>
                           <l>So furiouſely they rage:</l>
                           <l>Still crauing more, the more they haue:</l>
                           <l>What may their luſt aſſagwe?</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>So that they doe, as the <hi>Tragedian</hi> teſtifieth, <hi>drinke poiſon in golde:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Sen. in Thy.</note> or as <hi>Midas,</hi> whome the Poets fained to haue deſired of the Gods one petition, the which being graunted him, <hi>hee vviſhed
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:14967:24"/>that whatſoever he might touch ſhould bee turned into golde;</hi> which he obtaining purchaſed nothing thereby but his owne deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction. For when he ſhould feede, his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> (by reaſon of his former requeſt) beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming ſo hard a me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>, might well choake his, but never nouriſh him. This was ſet downe to ſignifie how much harme they procure vnto themſelues which purpoſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the heaping of wealth without regard, how it is got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten or how it ſhall be ſpent. For it is true that <hi>Iuvenall</hi> ſaith,
<q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Tantis parta malis, curâmaiore, metu<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan>
                           </l>
                           <l>Servantur: miſera eſt magus cuſtodia cenſus.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q> 
                     <hi>that is,</hi>
                     <q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>Ill gotten goods, are kept with greater care and feare:</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Great charge of wealth the miſers hart doth break &amp; teare. Beſides the wrongfull getting of them, and the great care that he hath in keeping of them, there is as great daunger in the evill vſing of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: either in not vſing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at al, but hording the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp to the hurt of many: or elſe in imploying of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> otherwiſe, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ought to be imployed. They that haue great ſtore of goods, and vſe them not at al, keepe them cloaſe, either becauſe they know not what to doe with them, or elſe becauſe they cannot find in their hartes to deparr with them. For the firſt ſort they are like vnto them that haue good horſes in their ſtables (as <hi>Iſocrates</hi> ſaith) and know not how to ride the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, whereby for want of vſe they become altogither vnprofirable. And as for the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſort, that haue no deſire to vſe their goods, though they know how to do it; they are not very vnlike vnto the <hi>ſhe-Ape</hi> which makes ſo much of her young-ons, that, with continual claſping of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhe many times cruſheth them to death: ſo theſe covetous crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures (that know how to vſe their good, and wil not) do ſo claſpe it, and hide it in their coaffers, that with the cloaſe keeping ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of they doe (as it were) cruſh it to death, for that they burie it in the ſepulcher of forgetfulneſſe, and vnprofitableneſſe. So then it is the eſtimation that we make of riches, which maketh a man either happy or vnhappy in the getting, in the hauing, and in the vſing of his goods. For vnleſſe his minde be his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derator
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14967:24"/>therein, there is no law, but the law of Reaſon, that can limitte his deſires.<note place="margin">Plutarch. in Vit. Lycurgi.</note> 
                     <hi>Lycurgus</hi> made a lawe amonge the <hi>Lacede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monians</hi> to take away their coyne of golde and ſilver, allowing them only coyne made of iron; thinking that he thereby ſhould haue brought them to deſpiſe and contemne coyne by the baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of that mettall; yet all this could not baniſh covetouſnes out of the cittie. For, their mindes being baſely bent, they were aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well in loue and liking with the baſer, as vvith the better mettalls. Take away from a man all his vvealth, yet you cannot take from him his covetouſneſſe. For that remaineth ſtill in his minde. If he hath little, hee deſireth much, if hee haue much, hee deſireth more: ſo that deſire is the fuell, that ſetteth his minde ſtill on fire. If ſome men doubt vvhy GOD giueth plenty of goodes vnto the badde, who know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not hovve to vſe them; and taketh it from the good, that can vſe them vvell; <hi>Auguſtine</hi> vvill aunſvvere them that <hi>if GOD ſhoulde giue his temporall bleſſinges onely vnto the good,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Auguſt. de verb. Dom. Serm. <hi>12.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>the evill vvoulde thinke that hee ought to be glorified onely for this and nothinge elſe.</hi> Againe, if hee ſhoulde giue them vnto the evill and vvicked onelie, the vveake vvoulde bee af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraide to bee converted, leaſt that they thereby ſhoulde vvante. If it ſhoulde bee taken from the evill, then they vvoulde thinke that this onely ſhoulde bee their puniſhment. From the good hee often taketh it, that they ſhoulde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire better thinges; vvhich they haue not common with the vvicked. Now that thou maieſt make a right vſe of this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, in waighing hovve thou haſt gotten, and how thou doeſt ſpende thy wealth, obſerue alwaies this, that in thy rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable care to obtaine ſufficiencie, thou keepe vnto thy ſelfe a ſafe conſcience not to wronge them, vvith vvhome thou doeſt deale: and that thou grovve not into to much loue with thy wealth; in the diſpenſation thereof thou oughteſt alſo to vſe Iuſtice vnto thy ſelfe in obſerving theſe fowre circumſtaunces, <hi>to VVhome, VVhou, VVherefore,</hi> and <hi>Hovve thou beſtovveſt thy vvealth;</hi> vvhich if thou perfourme, then haſt thou wel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, <hi>who thou art in the ſtate of thy wealth.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:14967:25"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. 4.</hi> The Conſideration of thy ſelfe, who thou art in the ſtate of thy calling and Authoritie.</head>
                  <p>FOr the Conſideration of thy ſelfe <hi>who thou art in thy calling and dignitie;</hi> either thy eſtate is honourable &amp; worſhipful, or meane.<note place="margin">Two ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies vnto an honora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble eſtate. The firſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie.</note> If it be honourable, then haſt thou two great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries to aſſaile thee; the one without thee; the other within thee: that without thee is <hi>Envy:</hi> that within thee, is <hi>pride.</hi> Thy externall enemy, Envie, is ever feeding and gnaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on thy felicity, ſo that it is impoſſible for thee to eſcape Envies iawes; and that eſpecially, if by thy vertues thou bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced and brought to an higher calling. For then thou ſhalt be ſure to be ſet vpon on al ſides by this externall enemy.<note place="margin">Ariſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Top. &amp; <hi>2</hi> li. Eth. ca <hi>7.</hi>
                     </note> For <hi>Envie</hi> is (as it is defined) a grieving and a grudging at other mens proſperity and happineſſe. There are certaine degrees, by which Envy doth worke againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that are envied by reaſon of their high callings come vnto by their good deſerts.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt is a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret murmuring, when they repine at his wel-doing, whom they hate and would faine diminiſh his praiſe and glory.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond is, when by detraction they ſeeke to depriue him of his good name.<note place="margin">Ad Heren.</note> Of ſuch <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith, <hi>that they by other mens diſpraiſe doe hunt after their owne commendations.</hi>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third, is when they do reioice in the adverſe fortune and fal of him, that hath beene advanced for his vvorth and worthineſſe.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The laſt is an evill affection and inward hatred,<note place="margin">T. de Orat.</note> vvhich they beare, grieving at the excellency of another man, and therefore ſeeke his confuſion. <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith, that men doe many times envy their equals, and their inferiours. For when they finde themſelues left behinde, they are grieved that they are out-gone by them: and very often doe they envy their ſuperiours, and that the more vehemently, by how much more highly they eſteeme or reckon of themſelues, and in their iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment doe paſſe the equalitie of common right by reaſon of the height of their dignitie and fortunes. So we ſee that <hi>too high
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:14967:25"/>a calling</hi> is accompanied with Envie, but chiefly, when arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancie and hauty behaviour is ioined with it. And although that Envie, this externall enemy, is very daungerous, yet is it neuer ſo hurtfull vnto a high eſtate or calling, as is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall adverſarie <hi>pride.</hi> For the forraine foe, Envie,<note place="margin">The ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d enemie.</note> may be eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly preuented, becauſe he commeth commonly to bidde the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile with his banners diſplaied, ſo that he may thereby be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned to be an enemy, and being knowne, may the more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily bee vvithſtood. But the domeſtical and inwarde enemie, Pride, doeth more ſecretlie aſſaile thee, and ſtirre vp civill warres within thine owne citty and vvithin thine owne ſelfe: he commeth vnawares to thee when thou knoweſt not of his comming: or if thou haſte knowledge thereof (which is but ſeldome) yet hee commeth not in the appearaunce and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of an enemy, but as a friend. For hee maketh thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that hee commeth to mainetaine thine honor, reputation, &amp; credit: &amp; therefore, not fearing or ſuſpecting him, thou canſt the more hardly reſiſt him. And pride, this inwarde enemy, is ſo much the more perilous (as one ſaith) then other enemies, <hi>becauſe other vices haue power in our evill doinges;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Aug. lib. de nat. &amp; gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia.</note> 
                     <hi>but this doeth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede and taketh ſtrength and full growth of our good actions and beſt deedes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Beſides theſe two forenamed adverſaries,<note place="margin">A third e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemie.</note> an high eſtat or cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling hath yet another enemy no leſſe dangerous then the tvvo former, which is, the <hi>flattery</hi> and <hi>diſsimulation</hi> of Paraſites: and ſurelie there is no man advaunced to any great calling, but ſhall be attended with ſuch hypocrites, which are rather <hi>followers of his fortunes, then of himſelfe;</hi> and are alwaies ready to applaude even his vvorſt actions, as honourable and vertuous: whereby they blindefolde him, and in the ende drowne him in the deepe and daungerous pit of <hi>miſbeliefe:</hi> neither will ſuch ſoothing fellowes giue him any incouragement to vndertake any vertuous acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or laudable exerciſe. For they holde that no pollicy, ſith they finde it beſt to followe him in his owne humors, vvhich they take to bee the onely way to come by his loue and favour: ſo that by theſe meanes great ſtates, and men of high place and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:14967:26"/>calling are ſooneſt corrupted in their conditions: and as, when they doe amiſſe, few men dare tell them their faultes; ſo their flatterers will be ready to make their faultes ſeeme no faults vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them: whereby ſuch followers make them worſe then of themſelues they would be.</p>
                  <p>Novv to vvithſtand theſe ſtrong aſſaultes, &amp; to ſaue thy ſelfe from ſuch dangerous invaſions of three ſo mighty impediments to the knowledge of thy ſelfe in the ſtate of thy calling, as are <hi>Envie, Pride,</hi> and <hi>Flattery;</hi> vſe theſe weapons to defend thee: a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Envie,</hi> vſe <hi>Vertue;</hi> againſt <hi>Pride</hi> and <hi>Ambition,</hi> vſe <hi>humility;</hi> and againſt <hi>Diſſimulation,</hi> vſe <hi>Diſcretion,</hi> to make difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene faithfull and flattering followers, and this may bee a marke for any generous minde, among ſuch as follow him. The faithfull and ſuch as deſire his honour and credit, will not ſpare to tell him his faultes; but the flatterer will footh him in all his doings. This if thou carry in thy remembrance, and put in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, then haſt thou well conſidered <hi>who thou art in, thy eſtate and calling.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:14967:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>THE THIRD SECTION OF</hi> the firſt part of the Conſideration of humane Condition.</head>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. 1.</hi> The Conſideration of thy ſelfe what manner of man thou art, firſt as touching thy learning.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He thirde and laſt point of Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion concerning the knowledge of thy ſelfe is, <hi>what manner of man thou art.</hi> For as the ſecond pointe of Conſideration (which is, <hi>who thou art</hi>) doth appertaine to the knowledge of of the body, with the ornamentes that doe belong to the outward eſtate therof: ſo this laſt point of Conſideration (which <hi>is, what manner of man thou art</hi>) doth chiefly containe the true vnderſtanding of thoſe things, which do adorne the inwarde eſtate of the minde. To attaine to the true knowledge whereof, it behoueth to haue the helpes of the <hi>intellectuall, morall,</hi> and <hi>theologicall vertues.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>6.</hi> Eth. ca <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note> The intellectuall vertues are ſaide of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> to be fiue viz. <hi>Art, Prudence, Science, Sapience,</hi> &amp; <hi>Intelligence.</hi> Intelligence is defined to bee <hi>the habite of principles;</hi> Science is ſaid to be the <hi>habite of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">lib <hi>6</hi> Ethic. Eth. ca. <hi>6.</hi> &amp; cap. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note> by which we learne to diſtinguiſh <hi>truth</hi> from <hi>falſhood.</hi> By theſe, to gither with Arte, Prudence, and Sapience (which are alſo partes of the intellectuall habite, of ſome called the intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectuall vertue) wee learne thoſe grounds that doe leade vs to the more perfect rules of pacifying our inordinate paſſions. For it is ſaide that <hi>knowledge and learning doe mollifie mens manners.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ovid. lib. <hi>2.</hi> de Pont.</note> But thou oughteſt chiefly to knowe what kinde of Arte, and what knowledge it is, that can amend the minde of man, &amp; then to follow the ſame. For there are ſome Artes, that when they be learned with great labour, yet are more hurtful the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> profitable: &amp;
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:14967:27"/>there are ſome Artes (as they are oftentimes vſed) vnneceſſary, and ſome altogeather vnlawfull.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Thoſe that are vnneceſſary be ſuch, as yeeld no commodity or profit to the publike weale, nor yet much to the private vſe of him that doth exerciſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: as the vaine vſe of <hi>Logick</hi> and <hi>Rhetoricke,</hi> when he that hath ſome inſight in them; hath not yet Reaſon how to vſe them: ſo that he maketh himſelfe like to the prattling &amp; prating <hi>Pye,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ovid. de Ph.</note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Poet ſpeaketh thus:
<q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>Picaloquax varias modulatur gutture voces</l>
                           <l>Scurrils ſtrepitu quic quid et audit, ait.</l>
                        </lg>
                     </q> 
                     <hi>which is,</hi>
                     <q>
                        <lg>
                           <l>
                              <hi>The pratling</hi> Pye <hi>faines every kind of voice,</hi>
                           </l>
                        </lg>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>And what ſhe heares, ſhe ſpeakes with chattering noiſe. Theſe Artes are not in themſelues vnneceſſary, although for want of the right vſe of them, they may be made vnneceſſary &amp; vnprofitable.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Other Artes there are, that haue more pleaſure then profitable vſe in them, and in their owne natures are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing or very little neceſſary, <hi>as Muſicke</hi> and the like: yet I know that the louers and practiſers thereof, will frame reaſons to prooue the profitte and neceſſity of them.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> There are alſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Artes, which are not onely vnneceſſary, but are alſo alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather vnprofitable and vnlawfull: as the vſe of that part of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologie</hi> which ſome call <hi>Medicinary,</hi> wherein they would ſeeme to ſet downe the certaine times of death, and life; of barenneſſe, and plenty; of warre, and peace; of mariages, of peſtilence, and the like future accidents. This Arte in it ſelfe, is both vnneceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, vnprofitable, vnlawfull, and vncertaine. For, as <hi>Cornelius Agrippa</hi> (one that was much giuen to that ſtudy in his youth,<note place="margin">Corn. de van ſcien.</note> and very excellently well ſeene therein) ſaith: <hi>Aſtrologie hath nothing in it elſe but meere trifles, Poets fables, much and monſtrous forgery and faining, vvherewith they haue imagined that the heaven is repleniſhed.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Hier de nat.</note> Of whome another learned man ſaith, <hi>that theſe be they, which lifte themſelues vp againſt the knowledge of all that is done, promiſing vnto themſelues a fained knowledge, and referring the event of all thinges vnto the riſing, falling, and courſe of the ſtarres, following therein their Mathematicall errours.</hi> But we wil leaue theſe, as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:14967:27"/>and altogither vncertaine; and not worthy to bee rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned or eſteemed of as an Arte.<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>6.</hi> Cap <hi>4.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> doth define an Arte to be a <hi>habite of doing with true reaſon.</hi> That therefore which hath no truth, nor true principles or certaine grounds, can be no Arte. But, to come vnto thoſe Artes which are both profitable and neceſſary, we may doe well to conſider firſt, that Artes are ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther liberall, or illiberall and Manuary. The liberall are ſaide to be the <hi>Seaven ſciences;</hi> and they may be called liberall, becauſe they require a liberal minde to be beſtowed on them, that is free from other cares, free from paſſions, free from ſordiditie. The other Artes, which are Manuary, although they do not ſo much adorne the minde of man, yet are they neceſſary for the vſe of man, and they ſuſtaine his neceſſities, keeping him from idlenes, which is the <hi>cancker of the minde:</hi> yet omitting thoſe Manuarie Artes, as matters that doe not of themſelues much beautifie the minde, wee vvill ſay ſomewhat concerning the knowledge of the other Artes, which are called the <hi>liberall Sciences,</hi> whereby it ſhall be ſeene what manner of men they are, that attaine to the knowledge of them, and to be perfect <hi>Artiſtes.</hi> And firſt, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the obtaining of thoſe Sciences; it hath beene a queſtion betweene Philoſophers of former ages, <hi>whither knowledge, vertue,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Whither vertue and knowledge be in vs by Nature.?</note> 
                     <hi>and ſcience were in vs by nature, or that it came vnto vs by ſtudie and exerciſe:</hi> wherein <hi>Platoes</hi> opinion was diſallowed and reiected of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> and others. For <hi>Plato</hi> his poſition was this, that the ſoule and minde of man was at his firſt creation adorned and inveſted with all ſcience, vertue, and knowledge, but that by reaſon of the infirmities of the body, it is (as hee ſaid) dulled &amp; dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with forgetfulneſſe and ignorau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: ſo that whatſoever man learneth afterwards it is but (as it were) a <hi>calling to remembrance,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Scientia (ait Plato) eſt reminiſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tia: ſcire eſt reminiſci.</note> and a <hi>renewing</hi> or <hi>reſtoring of that, which firſt he knew.</hi> But <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> that famous Philoſopher, is an adverſarie to this opinion. For he doth not acknowledge any ſuch abſolute excellency in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſeth that there are in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by nature certaine ſeeds and ſparkles of knowledge. And vve are ſaide to know,<note place="margin">Ariſt lib. <hi>2.</hi> Ethic. cap. <hi>1.</hi>
                     </note> and to haue ſcience by <hi>Definition,</hi> and <hi>Demonſtration.</hi> The Definition, and Demonſtration we doe gather from <hi>Particulars.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Omnis do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrina et om.</note> For out
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:14967:28"/>of <hi>Individualls</hi> we gather the Definition of the <hi>Speciall:</hi> and out of the <hi>Specialls,</hi> wee gather the definition of the <hi>Generall.</hi> But theſe Definitions and principles of demonſtration are not fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or ſettled in the firſt frame and foundation of Naturc. For by helpe of the Phantaſy, which doth ſtirre vp and offer vnto the minde the <hi>Idëas</hi> or imagination of things, the Minde doth ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the eſſence and qualities of thinges, which was not at the firſt perceiued or planted therein. It may be conceiued that <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to</hi> imagined that there ſhould be abſolute knowledge in man by nature, by reaſon that he reade (as ſome haue ſuppoſed) the firſt booke of <hi>Moſes,</hi> vz. <hi>Geneſis,</hi> whereof his workes doe ſavour ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what: and finding therein that man at the firſt vvas created ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely good,<note place="margin">Geneſ. Cap. <hi>1</hi>
                     </note> according to the likenes of him that created him, he was moued to imagine and thinke (as you haue heard) that he knew althings at the firſt, never remembring, or little regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to examine further of his <hi>fall:</hi> and how Man, deſiring to know good and evill (whereof he was ignorant, and therefore knew not all things) did thereby looſe that light of knowledge, which was originally ingraffed in him; whereby alſo all his po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity were and are plunged in the ſea of ignorance, as a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment paide on them, and on vs all for our firſt Parents diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. And although that <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> ſeemeth to refute <hi>Platoes</hi> rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of mans perfect knowledge by Nature, yet he himſelfe af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmeth that <hi>all Doctrine and all diſcipline proceedeth out of a praeexe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent knowledge.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ariſt. Lib. <hi>1.</hi> Poſter. Cap. <hi>1</hi>
                     </note> Whereby he might ſeeme in ſome ſorte to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent with <hi>Platoes</hi> concluſion. Yet this is to be vnderſtood that, that knowledge, which we haue is praeeiſtent, yet not in vs, but in them, from whome vvee doe receiue it. Which is made plaine by an other plaice in the ſame Author, where he ſaith: that, that <hi>doctrine &amp; ſcience proceedeth from man vnto man according to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon which the teacher hath vnto him that is taught:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Idem. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Poetriae.</note> this is a proofe that it commeth not by Nature, but by inſtruction.</p>
                  <p>But now to to conclude this point of Conſideration of know<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledge and learning, vve ought to knowe that the beginning &amp; ending of true knowledge and learning is <hi>to know our ſelues.</hi> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by how much more thy knowledge and learning doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bound,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:14967:28"/>by ſo much more ought thy humility to exceede: leaſt, forgetting thy ſelfe, thy knowledge and thy learning doe little benefite thee. Which rules if thou alwaies remember, then haſt thou conſidered thy ſelfe aright <hi>what manner of man thou art touching thy knowledge and learning.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>The conſideration of thy ſelfe what manner of man thou art in thy vviſedome. <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>HAVING conſidered thy ſelfe. <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hat manner of man thou art concerning thy knowledge in learning,</hi> as in Artes &amp; ſciences: it commeth next in courſe that thou ſhouldeſt conſider what manner of man thou art in thy <hi>vviſedome</hi> (for Wiſedome is ſaide alſo to be one of the intellectuall Habites) &amp; this by ſome is divided into two partes, that is; into <hi>prudence</hi> and <hi>ſapience. Prudence</hi> (as they affirme) is the knowledge of humane affaires onely;<note place="margin">Aug lib. de Trin. Cicer. lib. <hi>4.</hi> Tuſc.</note> but <hi>Sapience</hi> pertaineth to the knowledg of things both divine and humane: which is the cauſe that wee imitate divine things, and all humane inferiour matters are lead by the force thereof. Therefore if ſome men eſteeme Prudence (vvhich is commonly called <hi>Pollicy</hi>) to bee the chiefeſt parte of Wiſedome: yet hovve ſhorte this Prudence or humane polli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie is of that <hi>true vviſedome,</hi> vvhich conteineth the knowledg of things divine and humane, vve may meaſure it in this, that by how much the heavens are higher then the earth; by ſo much the knowledg of heavenly things is more worthy, and more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent then the knowledg of humane affaires &amp; earthly things.<note place="margin">Plut. lib. de morals ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute.</note> Prudence alſo is vnperfect and vncertaine being (as a wiſe Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher affirmeth) many times drowned in things full of errours and of turbulency, and it is conſtrained to bee coupled with thinges caſuall, to vſe Conſultation in matters doubtefull, which being done, it muſt vſe the helpe of thinges vnreaſonable for aſſiſtaunce. As touching the partes of Prudence, which are reakoned to bee <hi>Reaſon, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding, Circumspection</hi> and
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:14967:29"/>the like, as they are good helpes to furniſh and ſet foorth the praiſe of Prudence; ſo are they but ſeldome ſeene to ſome &amp; concurre altogither in one: or if any one doeth attaine to that excellency of Prudence, ſo as he doe poſſeſſe al the parts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, yet doth it ſerue but to ſet before him heapes of cares, and <hi>Labyrinthes</hi> of difficulties: ſo that the workes of Prudence and humane Pollicy may very well be compared to the <hi>Spyder,</hi> vvho taketh great paines, and vſeth great arte (in her kinde) to vveaue her webbe, which when it is finiſhed, doth ſerue to no other vſe, but to catch ſome few little fearefull flies: as for the great flies they either goe by the weake webbe, or through it without any danger at all: and many times after all the paines taken therein, either the violence of windes, or of ſome other fowle weather on the ſoddaine doth deface and deſtroy that well-wrought web. So falleth it out ful often with the workma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſhip of humane Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licie. For when a man by Prudence and humane Pollicie hath faſhioned ſome cunning, fine, or artificial web (faire to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde appearance of the worlde) and that withall the deviſes, that a curious and a painefull conceipt can frame; yet (in a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner) it is but as if it vvere a vvorke to catch flies in the aire, or (in deede) fooles with vaine allurementes vppon the land: as for the greater flies, which are as ſtrong and cunning as the Spider her ſelfe, they will catch the Spider as ſone, or rather, then the Spider ſhall intercept or intangle them. Admitte thou (oh worldly Politique man, whoſoeuer thou art) that thou haſt wouen thy webbe with the threede of Prudence very ſtrongly, procuring thy ſelfe great patrimonies, honorable alliaunce, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments many, and high advancements: yet perchance on the ſuddaine, and when thou thinkeſt leaſt of it, ſome ſuddaine ſtormes of ill fortunes will fal vpon thee, and ſo tumble thee in thy well-wrought webbe of Prudence and Pollicy, that it wil be all to rent and torne in pieces: or what thou dreameſt leaſt of, the laſt Conquerour <hi>Death,</hi> he commeth, and (as an vnplacable enemy) breaketh in pieces thy whole web ſo prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly wrought and ſo politiquely finiſhed to thine owne content, to the greate ioy of thy friends, &amp; to the wonder &amp; admiration of moſt men.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:14967:29"/>But leaſt we ſhould be thought to ſette aſide all eſtimation, and to make no accoumpt of Prude<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, or humane Pollicy, which in worldly matters carrieth ſo great a ſtroke amongſt men, it were not amiſſe to examine the partes of Prudence and to eſtimate thereby the value thereof: and they are reakoned by ſome to be, Reaſon, Circumſpection, Counſaile, and the like.<note place="margin">Macrob. in Com. ſomn. Scip.</note> Nowe <hi>Reaſon</hi> as it is a part of Prudence (for Reaſon ſometimes is taken for the principal facultie of the ſoule &amp; ſo it is the <hi>ſubiect</hi> of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and other Intellectual Vertues) <hi>is the diſcourſe of the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding by which the vniverſall principles of thinges that may be done, are applied vnto particular things which are to be done, though diverſe &amp; vncertaine.</hi> And ſo Reaſon &amp; Vnderſtanding are not diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed as two diverſe <hi>povvers,</hi> but as two diverſe <hi>actes</hi> of the ſame power. For, <hi>to reaſon,</hi> is to proceede from one vnderſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto another, yet every kinde of Reaſoning is not that part of Prudence, which we ſpeake of in this place, becauſe, if wee take <hi>Reaſoning</hi> largely in that ſenſe, as it is a proceeding from principles vnto concluſions, as in <hi>Syllogiſmes,</hi> and in the <hi>Arte of arguing either Rhetorically, or Logically;</hi> this is rather to bee reac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned as an <hi>Arte of Reaſoning,</hi> then <hi>Reaſon</hi> it ſelf. For if Reaſon did conſiſt in ſpeaking eloquently, or in diſputing ſubtilly, then the idle Rhetoricia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and the ſubtile Sophyſt ſhould be moſt poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt, and beſt indued with Reaſon; and conſequently, ſhoulde enioy chiefly that part of Prudence. <hi>Iſidorus</hi> ſaith, that <hi>Diſcreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> is the provident fore-ſeer in iudging the cauſes of things,<note place="margin">Iſidor. in Sin</note> &amp; the reaſon of moderating mens mindes: according to which ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>plication Reaſon is applied or defined by him to be, <hi>the order of doing things proceeding from their cauſe,</hi> as, <hi>what, in what place,</hi> and, <hi>how thou ſhouldeſt doe, speake, and vnderſtand.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Next vnto Reaſon,<note place="margin">Tho Agu. Sec. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>Circumſpection</hi> claimeth a place in the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectes and operation of Prudence: which is defined to bee the <hi>attention of circumſtances in morall matters:</hi> and if it be an attention of circumſtances, then it muſt conſider what doth belong vnto place, perſon, and time: and not ſo much to followe the time in all things. For that were irreligious, although ſome Politici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans preſcribe that as a good rule, &amp; very requiſite to be obſerued
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:14967:30"/>of prudent men: but <hi>to yeelde vnto neceſſity</hi> is a rule, which both Reaſon and Circumſpection doth teach vs, becauſe we are not thereby conſtrained to forſake the boundes and law of honeſty. In this, <hi>Coniecture</hi> comes in as an harbinger, to lodge the Circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of our Circumſpection, and to prepare the way to <hi>Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> as <hi>what, when,</hi> and <hi>how,</hi> things ought to be done: neither may there be too much Circumſpection vſed (for that it often-times turneth to iealouſie, or ſuſpition without cauſe) &amp; as the <hi>Comoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> concludeth:<note place="margin">Plaus. in Cap.</note> 
                     <hi>he, that is moſt circumspect, leaſt he be deceived, is ſcarce circumspect mough, when he is moſt circumspect,</hi> and this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident man, when he is moſt carefull, is moſt commo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly caught. After Circumſpection commeth <hi>Counſaile,</hi> bringing with it the <hi>Concluſion of Prudence.</hi> For after Counſaile there is nothing to be performed but the execution thereof, which is the end &amp; event of thinges.<note place="margin">Cic. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Rhet. Jdem lib. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note> This Counſaile is called the <hi>inquiſitiue appetite of doing things thought vpon with Reaſon:</hi> and the ſame author ſaith, that <hi>it is the ſubtile foreſeeing of the minde in cauſes to be examined or gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned:</hi> to the attaining wherof <hi>Seneca</hi> giveth ſingular precepts,<note place="margin">Senecatract. de virtute.</note> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; if thou deſire to be prudent, intende and extend thy fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight to future things, and ponder what may come to paſſe: let thoſe things that muſt needes be done of thee, be (as it were) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee alwaies and in thy ſight, For he that is wiſe, ſaith not, <hi>I thought this could not be;</hi> he doubteth not what ſhall happen, but expecteth and looketh for it; he doth not ſuſpect it, but he doth looke and provide to prevent it: ſeeke therfore (ſaith he) if thou wilt proue wiſe in deed, the cauſe of every thing, &amp; having fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the beginning, conſider and bethinke with thy ſelfe what may be the end thereof. Theſe preceptes that concerne Counſaile (though they are excellent) yet notwithſtanding are eaſier to be given, then to be followed or put in practiſe and accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: this is the ſubſtance of all difficult matters and ſuch as haue neede of Conſultation; vvherein we finde by common experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that every man can more readily, and with words more li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally adviſe another man what he ſhould doe, then if the caſe did concerne himſelfe. For anxiety and doubt of doing that, which a man may dammage himſelfe by, doth diverſe times ſo
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:14967:30"/>diſtract his ſenſes betweene <hi>feare</hi> and <hi>forethinking,</hi> that his iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thereby is much and mightely darkened. In Counſaile therefore, whether it be for a man his owne ſelfe, or for his friend <hi>a due Deliberation</hi> of any thing in doubt is alwaies requiſite. For, as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith, there are two things,<note place="margin">Sen. in Proverb.</note> which are contrary and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe to good Counſaile, that is <hi>feſtination,</hi> or overmuch haſte; and <hi>Anger,</hi> or choller. And the ſame author adviſeth every man to deliberate long of that thing, which he muſt do &amp; performe, though it were but once.</p>
                  <p>If thou wilt vnderſtande, <hi>what manner of man thou art in owing and poſſeſſing of Prudence or worldly Pollicie, or whither thou be happie or vnhappy in having thereof,</hi> let this be vnto thee as a certaine rule, <hi>that it is, as all other worldly bleſſings are vnto thee.</hi> Gold is good, if it be turned to good vſes: yea it is alſo euil, &amp; maketh thee evil to, if thou doe not vſe it vvel. Such is the effect of Prudence or hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Pollicy: it vvorketh alſo according as thou doeſt vſe it. For as <hi>Seneca</hi> ſaith, if a prudent man exceede his bounds,<note place="margin">Sen. lib. de benef.</note> he ſhevveth himſelfe to be a ſubtile ſearcher of thinges hidden; a finder and a follovver of al faultes, euil, full of pride, crafty, an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to innocency, a commender of crimes, and in concluſion, accompted of by al men as of a lewd perſon, vngodly, and very vvicked. And this is true, that men, vvhich are by nature poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique and vvel practiſed, or of great experience in vvorldly mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, if they follovv not a right courſe, apply their heartes and vvittes to that vvhich is good, keeping themſelues vvithin the compaſſe of <hi>honeſtie</hi> and <hi>a good Conſcience,</hi> they are of all people moſt pernitious and moſt dangerous to converſe, or to be dealt vvithall.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:14967:31"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> The Conſideration of thy ſelfe, what manner of man thou art touching the perturbations of the minde.</head>
                  <p>THe <hi>Minde</hi> of man may bee compared vnto <hi>a compaſſe</hi> or a <hi>carde,</hi> by which the ſea-men do direct their courſe. Which if it be truely drawne, &amp; the points therof perfectly obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; then the paſſengers moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly do come ſafe &amp; quietly vnto the hauen &amp; harbor, where they would be, but if the Pilote do not place his compaſſe aright, &amp; perfectly obſerue the points thereof, then vſually the ſhip, wherein he ſaileth, is driuen out of the right courſe, and happily runneth againſt the rockes. Such is mans eſtate in this miſerable world, which is <hi>the ſea,</hi> wherein hee ſaileth: his <hi>minde</hi> is his <hi>co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe,</hi> &amp; if that be not vprightly placed &amp; directed by the points of Reaſon, then the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe ſerueth to no vſe, but he is caried a wrong way with the violent ſtormes of <hi>paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions</hi> &amp; <hi>perturbations</hi> of the minde againſt the rocks of miſeries &amp; many miſfortunes in this world. Seeing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that a quiet, a ſetled, &amp; a contented minde is the only meane &amp; compaſſe to carry vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the croſſes &amp; calamities of this worlde, &amp; to convay vs vnto the harbor &amp; haven of happines: ſeeing alſo that the Perturba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Minde do much hinder the true courſe of tranquilli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty &amp; of felicity in this life: It were not amiſle to examine the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces &amp; paſſages by which theſe Perturbations do overwhelme the minde of man, which being found out, it wil be the more ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie to avoide the inconveniences and dangerous effects thereof.</p>
                  <p>Divers and very doubtfull haue bin the opinions of auncient Philoſophers co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the Perturbations of the minde, as what they ſhould be, &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence they ſhould proceede? whether they were only actiue or paſſiue qualities, or elſe mixed of both? what the number of them ſhould be? Whether al kindes of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbations were to be reiected? with diuers other ſuch doubtes, wherein they did much diſter. And becauſe it doth very much concerne the knowledge of mans ſelfe <hi>what manner of man he is, to be informed touching the perturbations of the minde,</hi> we will ſay ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what therein.</p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:14967:31"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Zeno,</hi> being the principall of of the <hi>Stoicke</hi> Philoſophers doth define.<note place="margin">Cicero lib. <hi>4.</hi> Tuſcu. queſt</note> 
                     <hi>Perturbation</hi> (as <hi>Cicero</hi> alleadgeth) <hi>to be an averſe commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the minde contrary to Reaſon.</hi> This definition ſome others haue ſeemed to diſlike. For they ſay that every kind of Pertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation is not altogeather averſe and contrary vnto Reaſon, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though moſt kinds of Perturbations be voide of Reaſon. Which <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> affirmeth, when he ſaith that <hi>A vertue is converſant about pleaſure and griefe.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ariſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Ethic cap. <hi>3.</hi>
                     </note> Alſo <hi>Epicurus</hi> alleadgeth that the chiefe felicity of man conſiſteth in <hi>pleaſure,</hi> wherein he is miſconceiued of many; for he placeth this pleaſure wholy in vertue and vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous actions, and not in the pleaſures of the body, as divers do vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truely vnderſtand him. Neither doe the ſtrict rulers of Theolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie abſolutely take away all kindes of Perturbations from the minde of man, for as <hi>Saint Auguſtine</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Auguſt. de Civita. Dei.</note> the cittizens of the holy and heavenly citty do feare, deſire, grieue, and reioyce, and yet becauſe their loue is right, they haue alſo their affections vpright.</p>
                  <p>Likevviſe the heroicall vertues as <hi>fortitude</hi> and <hi>magnanimitie</hi> haue ſome of the Perturbatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the minde, as their inſtrume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts for the obiects of them: as honor, glory, &amp; victory are never ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained or attempted but thorow the proſecutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſome of thoſe Perturbations. But leaſt our meaning might be miſtaken, and that ſome ſhould ſuppoſe that we goe about to allow al the Per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>turbations. of the minde as either neceſſary or tollerable, we will diſtinguiſh of Perturbations, and conſider of their courſe ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in reſpect of the <hi>ſubiect,</hi> in which they are, or the <hi>obiectes,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout which they are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>verſant, &amp; the <hi>end,</hi> to which they tende. The <hi>ſubiects,</hi> in which they are, are of two ſorts:<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt <hi>Creatures wanting Reaſon,</hi> as beaſts, which by naturall inſtinct doe feare that which may be hurtful vnto their kind, &amp; they deſire that, which is for the preſervation of their kinde. And in them theſe Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s are not againſt Reaſon, although the ſubiects, in which theſe Perturbations are, be voide of Reaſon. But the <hi>Stoickes</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that there are no Perturbations in beaſtes, yet the <hi>Peripa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tetickes</hi> and the <hi>Academickes</hi> alleage the contrary, that beaſtes haue by Nature a proanes to pleaſure and griefe, to loue and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:14967:32"/>following and forſaking: all which are properly called Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbations. The next <hi>ſubiect,</hi> in which theſe Perturbations are, may be Man himſelfe, and the Perturbations, wherewith he is poſſeſſed, may be either tollerable; or intollerable, according to the <hi>obiects,</hi> about which, and the <hi>end,</hi> to which they are dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. And there is ſome kinde of Perturbations in man not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly voide of Reaſon, but contrary to Reaſon. As when a man na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally indued with Reaſon, doth vſually yelde vnto vnreaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable actions, following his <hi>Concupiſcible Appetite</hi> in luſt, or the like vaine Pleaſures; or elſe the <hi>Iraſcible Appetite</hi> in anger, ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance and the like, being proane through the inſtigation of theſe Perturbations to do that, which tendeth vnto the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of his owne kinde: and theſe Perturbations are not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly contrary to Reaſon, but even altogither raiſed and blotted out of Reaſons bookes. There is an other kinde of Perturbation in man (as it may in ſome ſort ſo bee called) which yet worketh with, and by Reaſon, as that Delight, and Ioy, which we take in vertue, and vertuous actions; and that Diſpleaſure &amp; Offence, which we conceiue at the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that do vitiouſly behaue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. In this here is Delight, &amp; Diſpleaſure, which are reackoned as Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbations, and yet the groundes of them proceede from Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and worke with Reaſon, or at the leaſt, not contrary to Rea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
                  <p>Now next for the number of the Perturbations, they haue bin alwaies left vncertaine,<note place="margin">Plato. de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pub. li. <hi>9.</hi>
                     </note> and not agreed vpon. For <hi>Plato</hi> vvould haue them to be innumerable, when as he doth call the <hi>Concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible Appetite, a beaſt of many heads.</hi> For it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taineth deſire, delight, loue,<note place="margin">Cicero. lib. <hi>4.</hi> Tuſcul.</note> pleaſure, and others almoſt infinite. <hi>Cicero</hi> according to the opinion of the <hi>Stoickes</hi> affirmeth that there are foure firſt heades of the Perturbations, vnder which the reſt are placed, as <hi>griefe, feare, ioy, and luſts,</hi> He ſaith in that place that there are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained vnder <hi>griefe,</hi> Envie, Emulation, Oblectatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Bewailing, Carefulnes, Affliction, Deſperation and ſuch like. Vnder <hi>feare</hi> he putteth Slouth, Shame, Terror, Aſtoniſhment, and the like. Vnder <hi>pleaſure</hi> he placeth Delectation, Deſire, and many other, ſo that he ſetteth downe no certaine number of the Perturbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:14967:32"/>although he alloweth, as it were certaine roots, out of which the reſt ſhould ſpring But yet moſt do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent, that there are two foundations or fountaines, from whence the reſt of the Pertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bations doe proceede; that is, the <hi>Concupiſcible</hi> and the <hi>Iraſcible</hi> Appetites: the Perturbations following the <hi>Concupiſcible Appetite,</hi> are loue, hatred, deſire, delectation, and ſorow: ſo likewiſe the Perturbatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which appertaine to the <hi>Iraſcible Appetite,</hi> are hope, deſperation, feare, boldnes, diſdaine, preſumption, and the like.</p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Then as concerning the courſe of theſe two principall rootes of Perturbation with their particular baranches, if thou wouldſt know how they doe come or make entrance into the Minde of man, and thereby way with thy ſelfe, <hi>What manner of man thou art therein,</hi> know that there is no man liuing abſolutely free and cleare from all theſe Perturbations of the Minde, and although ſome men are more ſubiect vnto them then others are, yet there is not any, that is not moleſted with ſome of them. Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, it is more vſuall to men of ſome age and eſtate to bee incombred with ſome particular Perturbations, then to others. Alſo they are more incident to one ſexe then to an other. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe they come to ſome by <hi>Nature,</hi> and to other ſome by <hi>Acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent.</hi> As for exampleahe Concupiſcible Appetire with his ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall branches is more common, and yet not ſo continuall as is the Iraſcible. For to loue, to hate, to deſire, to delight, to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, are things common to al men, though not at all times. And they come more by Accident the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by Nature: And yet ſomtimes by both. But the Iraſcible Appetite with his particular partes doth much poſſeſſe many men by Nature; as ſome are from their cradell fearefull: ſome are by Nature angrie and waſhpiſh; ſome are alwaies impacient: ſome are never but preſumptuous &amp; the like. As touching the Perturbations proceeding from the Iraſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Appetite, ſome haue affirmed that they come of hote blood, ſtirred vp about the hearte, which doth kindle and inflame the ſpirites with an immagination of anger &amp; offence. And (as one ſaith) there are fiue degrees, by the which men are ſtirred vp to wrath &amp; anger; the firſt is, Man againſt himſelfe: the ſecond is man againſt ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: the third is againſt his ſuperiour power, as God: the fourth is againſt his inferiours, as beaſtes and other creatures
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:14967:33"/>without reaſon: the fifte is againſt thinges without life.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> As for the firſt, which is the anger, that man conceiueth againſt him. ſelfe: it may in ſome ſorte be lawfull and commendable, as when he is angrie with himſelfe for his offence committed in doing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny diſhoneſt thing: this anger is laweful, but vvhen he is angrie with himſelfe, becauſe he cannot doe that, which he woulde, or cannot haue that, which he deſireth, being thinges either im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible or vnprofitable to bee performed, or elſe vnlawfull or vnmeete to be deſired; this kinde of anger is againſt Reaſon.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The next, which is the wrath that one man conceiueth againſt an other, this may bee either tollerable or intollerable, as the cauſe thereof is, or as he, which is offended, doth'carrie and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haue himſelfe in the courſe of his wrath: the cauſe of anger may be ſuch, that to conceale it, were not commendable. For when a mans good name is take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> away vniuſtly by a ſlanderer or back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitter, to conceale this is not commendable: becauſe he that is ſlaundred, being ſilent, ſeemeth to condemne himſelfe; yet the anger that is conceiued in this caſe, ought not to extend pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently vnto extremity of revenge. For if the partie mooued may be ſatisfied with the confeſſion of his accuſer that he hath wron<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ged him, or that he can otherwiſe prooue himſelfe wronged, whereby the worlde is ſatisfied, that he was ſlaundred, his anger ought to be appeaſed.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Third kinde of anger, which is of man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his maker, is both irreligious and vnreaſonable, and may rather be called <hi>madnes,</hi> then <hi>anger.</hi> For it is like his condition, that throweth ſtones into the aire vpright, and ſtandeth ſtil, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til they fal vpon his owne head.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth, which is the anger of man againſt beaſtes, is but little more then beſtiall, when the vnreaſonable creature ſhalbe angry with the vnreaſonable.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The fift of man againſt things without life ſheweth that he wanteth that reaſon, which ſhould be the light of his owne life.</p>
                  <p>Somewhat ſhould be ſaide as concerning the cauſe &amp; courſe of the Concupiſcible Appetite, but becauſe we deſire to avoide tediouſnes, and that the ſhortnes of time alloweth no large diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, I will conclude with ſome ſhorte precept for the avoi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of theſe two perillous <hi>Appetites</hi> of the mind; which are the Iraſcible and the Concupiſcible Appetite. Therefore if thou
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:14967:33"/>wilt ſhunne thoſe two ſo cruel adverſaries vnto a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted mind, as are the Concupiſcible and Iraſcible Appetite, thou muſt firſt learne <hi>what maner of man thou art in ſuffering or in ſuppreſſing of theſe Appetites of the minde;</hi> thou muſt call vnto thy remembraunce &amp; knowledg the vſe of <hi>Intellectual, Moral</hi> &amp; <hi>Theological Vertues.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Next in place (but before in operation &amp; effect) are the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> vertues, which do incline and invite men to do things honeſt and lavvful: theſe do helpe much to quiet the Perturbations of the minde &amp; to make a man knovv vvhat manner of man he is. But eſpecially the ſowre Morall vertues, which are called Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall vertues, do much further the conquering of thoſe Paſſions: as <hi>Temperance, Prudence, Fortitude</hi> and <hi>Iuſtice.</hi> They are called Cardinall vertues, <hi>a Cardine,</hi> ſignifying the <hi>hindge of a doore:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe as on the hindge the gate is turned, ſhut and opened; ſo the heart of man, which is the hindge of the doore in doing all good actions, is opened to things honeſt, &amp; ſhut againſt things vnhoneſt by force of theſe vertues. And although thoſe fowre, called the Cardinal vertues, be of greateſt force, yet al the reſt do ſerue in ſome ſort to governe the Perturbations of the Minde, and to make a man know what manner of man he is: As <hi>Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence, Magnanimity, Liberality, Modeſty, Manſuetude, Vrba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, Affabilitie.</hi> Whereof ſome do reſpect the body with the Minde, ſome do direct the Minde moſt.</p>
                  <p>Thoſe, vvhich require the bodies aſſiſtaunce (although they haue wholy the mindes direction) are <hi>Fortitude</hi> and <hi>Magnanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie:</hi> ſome belong vnto the government of the ſenſes as <hi>Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce</hi> vnto the tvvo ſenſes of <hi>Touching</hi> and <hi>Taſting.</hi> But <hi>Continencie</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaineth to the moderating of all the ſenſes. Some others doe ſerue for direction of manners, as <hi>Affabilitie</hi> in vvords or ſpeech; <hi>Vrbanitie</hi> or civility in deedes. So by the helpe of thoſe Morall vertues thou maieſt learne to maſter the Perturbations of the Minde appertaining either to the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cupiſcible or ſraſcible Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite. For by Fortitude thou maieſt overcome <hi>Feare:</hi> by Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuetude thou maieſt conquere <hi>Impatience, anger,</hi> &amp; ſuch like; by Temperance and Continency thou maieſt ſubdue <hi>Immoderate deſires,</hi> as luſt and ſuch other like paſſions and Perturbations of the minde, vvhere vvith men are much overwhelmed. Yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:14967:34"/>
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertue</hi> is ſaide to bee <hi>a mediocrity betwixt two vices having the exceſſe on the one ſide,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ariſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Lib.</note> 
                     <hi>and the defect on the other;</hi> hovv hard then it is alwaies to keepe the <hi>Meane</hi> and not to fall on either ſide, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man may eaſily ſee and know. For as we ſee travellers, who haue a long iorney to make, ſometimes doe meete with many waies in one place, ſome turning on the right hand, ſome on the left, and others going out-right: yet of al theſe waies there is but one, which is the right vvay, and that often ſeemes to be the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likelieſt way, when that, which leadeth to his iournies end, is not ſo beaten a way, nor ſo much bending (as the paſſenger perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded himfelſe) vnto his right courſe: ſo fareth it with them that travell in the tedious iourney of this life: the <hi>world</hi> is our high vvay, vvhich hath in it many by-pathes, &amp; the poore paſſingers, that travel therein, are diuers times diſtracted, &amp; in much doubt for the choice of their way. For the faireſt way in appearaunce is not alwaies (nay it is ſeldome) the right way:<note place="margin">Xenoph. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Paed. Cyr.</note> &amp; the wrong waies are much more beaten and much more eaſie to finde then the true way. For if a man wil follow the foote ſteps of others exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, he ſhal finde a broad-beaten path, which is commonly the vvorſt, and the vvrong vvay. It is not the mediocrity, but it is the vvay that leadeth vnto the exceſſe, or to the defect. Therefore ſince it is ſo hard a matter to finde the right way in conquering the Perturbations of the minde, it behoueth euery man (if hee will be maſter ouer his owne Affections) to cal vnto his aide (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the <hi>Intellectuall</hi> &amp; <hi>Morall</hi> vertues before named) the <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicall</hi> vertues, which are <hi>Faith, Charitie, Pietie, Patience,</hi> and the like: by the power whereof (and the permiſſion and aſſiſtance of him that graunteth them) he may wel manage his owne minde, and all the Perturbations thereof. But becauſe the conſideratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hereof appertaineth to the knowledge of thoſe things, <hi>that are aboue,</hi> it muſt be leſt vnto that laſt point of Conſideration.</p>
                  <p>In the meane time thou maieſt (by that little which hath bin here laid downe) learne ſomewhat concerning <hi>the knowledge of thy ſelfe</hi> (which is the firſt of the fowre principall pointes of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration) and in this thou haſt ſeene ſomewhat, <hi>what, who, and what manner of man thou art.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:14967:34"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
